<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Felipe Martin's Blog</title><link href="https://fmartingr.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://fmartingr.com/feed.xml" rel="self"></link><id>urn:uuid:ceb84de2-e3c9-3d8c-8c2f-48a83004373d</id><updated>2024-04-28T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name></name></author><entry><title>Journey to K3s: Accessing from the Outside</title><link href="https://fmartingr.com/blog/2024/04/28/journey-to-k3s-accessing-from-the-outside/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2024-04-28T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name></name></author><id>urn:uuid:091a8e14-a349-36be-b114-cf7937945f87</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Up until now I have been working locally (on my home network). While that is enough for most of the services I'm running I need to access some of them from the outside. For example, I want to expose this blog to the internet and access Miniflux to read my RSS feeds on the go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few ways to achieve this but I have some specific requirements that I want to meet:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zero-trust approach&lt;/strong&gt;: I don't want to expose the services directly to the internet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Public services&lt;/strong&gt;: Other clients apart from me should be able to access some of the services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Home IP safety&lt;/strong&gt;: Don't directly expose my home IP address. (This is on par with #1, but I want to make it explicit).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On-transit encryption&lt;/strong&gt;: Full on transit encryption from the client to the cluster with no re-encryption in the middle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No Cloudflare. (Breaks #4)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No Tailscale. (Breaks #2, also there are other users at home and I don't want to have the Tailscale client running all the time).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does this leave me? A reverse proxy server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2024/04/28/journey-to-k3s-accessing-from-the-outside/healthcheck-360.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- readmore --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm going to setup &lt;a href="https://www.haproxy.org/"&gt;HAProxy&lt;/a&gt; in a separate external server to act as a reverse proxy that will connect to my home k3s cluster directly, but since the DNS records will point to this HAProxy server my home IP address will not be exposed. HAProxy won't be able to decrypt the traffic but leverage the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Server_Name_Indication"&gt;SSL SNI header&lt;/a&gt; to route the traffic back to the cluster for the allowed domains that I setup. This way I can have a zero-trust approach and have the traffic encrypted from the client to the cluster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, to start working I created a new VPS in &lt;a href="https://hetzner.cloud/?ref=gSMfCgZFSz1u"&gt;Hetzner Cloud&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;(affiliate link)&lt;/em&gt; and installed HAProxy in there, which is the easy part. Once the system is up to date and with the minimal services running I can start working on setting up HAProxy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="passthrough-traffic"&gt;Passthrough traffic&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Passthrough traffic is fairly simple, just create a &lt;em&gt;frontend&lt;/em&gt; that listens on port 443 and sends the traffic to the ssl &lt;em&gt;backend&lt;/em&gt; that check for SSL and sends data upstream to the k3s cluster. Since I'm are not decrypting the traffic &lt;a href="https://www.haproxy.com/documentation/haproxy-configuration-tutorials/load-balancing/tcp/"&gt;TCP mode&lt;/a&gt; is used to tunnel the traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm going to use &lt;a href="https://www.haproxy.com/documentation/haproxy-configuration-manual/latest/#4-option%20ssl-hello-chk"&gt;&lt;code&gt;ssl-hello-chk&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; option to ensure the traffic is SSL. This option checks if the first bytes of the connection are a valid SSL handshake, if not it will drop the connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;frontend k3s-01-ssl&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Listen on port 443 (HTTPS)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;bind *&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;443&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Use TCP mode, meaning that HAProxy won&amp;#39;t decrypt the traffic and just passthrough to the upstream server&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;mode tcp&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Enable advanced logging of TCP connections with session state and timers&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;option tcplog&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Send to the backend&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;use_backend k3s-01-ssl&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="na"&gt;backend k3s-01-ssl&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Use TCP mode, meaning that HAProxy won&amp;#39;t decrypt the traffic and just passthrough to the upstream server&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;mode tcp&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Balance the traffic between the servers in a round-robin fashion (not needed for a single server)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;balance roundrobin&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Retry at least 3 times before giving up&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;retries 3&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Check if the traffic is SSL&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;option ssl-hello-chk&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Send the traffic to the k3s cluster&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;server home UPSTREAM_IP&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;443 check&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id="force-ssl-redirect-http-to-https"&gt;Force SSL (redirect HTTP to HTTPS)&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since initially I'm not going to expose plain HTTP services I can just &lt;a href="https://www.haproxy.com/documentation/haproxy-configuration-tutorials/http-redirects/#sidebar"&gt;redirect&lt;/a&gt; all HTTP trafic to HTTPS: Just need to create a new frontend that listens on port 80 and redirects the traffic to the HTTPS frontend. This should work transparently for the client.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;frontend k3s-01-http&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Listen on port 80 (HTTP)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;bind *&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;80&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Use HTTP mode&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;mode http&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Redirect switching scheme to HTTPS&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;http-request redirect scheme https&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id="deny-non-allowed-domains"&gt;Deny non-allowed domains&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;For security reasons I want to deny access to all domains that are not in the allowed list: that is domains that I explicitly allow for outside access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm going to create a file &lt;code&gt;/etc/haproxy/allowed-domains.txt&lt;/code&gt; with the list of domains separated by newlines and use the &lt;a href="https://www.haproxy.com/documentation/haproxy-configuration-tutorials/core-concepts/acls/"&gt;&lt;code&gt;acl&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; directive to check if the domain is in the list abruptly droping the connection if it's not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The file &lt;code&gt;/etc/haproxy/allowed-domains.txt&lt;/code&gt; looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;# /etc/haproxy/allowed-domains.txt
miniflux.fmartingr.com
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new configuration options for the &lt;strong&gt;frontend&lt;/strong&gt; part. No changes needed on the backend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;frontend k3s-01-ssl&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# ... other configurations&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Allow up to 5 seconds to inspect the TCP request before giving up.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Required since HAProxy needs to inspect the SNI header to route the traffic.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;tcp-request inspect-delay 5s&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Accept the request only after the hello message is received (which should contain the SNI header).&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;tcp-request content accept if { req_ssl_hello_type 1 }&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Deny the request if the domain is not in the allowed list&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;acl allowed_domain req.ssl_sni -m end -i -f /etc/haproxy/allowed-domains.txt&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Send to the backend if the domain is allowed&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;use_backend k3s-01-ssl if allowed_domain&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once all this changes are in place I can restart the HAProxy service and the traffic should be routed to the k3s cluster so I can access the services from the outside without exposing my home IP address and have the traffic encrypted from the client to the cluster. Though not perfect this is a fairly simple and good setup, it requires manual labor but it's a good tradeoff for the requirements I have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Back when I set up Miniflux &lt;a href="/blog/2024/03/25/journey-to-k3s-deploying-the-first-service-and-its-requirements/#setting-up-an-external-ingress"&gt;I created an ingress specifically for external access&lt;/a&gt; that wasn't working since my cluster could not be reached by the ACME servers on the domain I set up. Now that I have HAProxy in place the domain can be setup to point to it and the traffic will be correctly routed to the cluster completing the configuration by requesting a certificate from Let's Encrypt and exposing the Ingress to the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>Journey to K3s: Basic Cluster Backups</title><link href="https://fmartingr.com/blog/2024/04/21/journey-to-k3s-basic-cluster-backups/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2024-04-21T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name></name></author><id>urn:uuid:a6b305e5-ba0d-3c77-b625-c71440c2129b</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There a time to deploy new services to the cluster, and there is a time to backup the cluster. Before I start depending more and more of the services I want to self-host it's time to start thinking about backups and disaster recovery. My previous server have been running with a simple premise: if it breaks, I can rebuild it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm going to try and keep that same simple approach here, theoretically if something bad happens I should be able to rebuild the cluster from scratch by backing up cluster snapshots and the data stored in the persistent volumes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2024/04/21/journey-to-k3s-basic-cluster-backups/longhorn-backups-360.jpg" alt="Longhorn screenshot displaying ongoing backups"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- readmore --&gt;

&lt;h2 id="cluster-resources"&gt;Cluster resources&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In my case I store all resources I create in a git repository (namespaces, helm charts, configuration for the charts, etc) so I can recreate them easily if needed. This is a good practice to have in place, but it's also a good idea to have a backup of the resources in the cluster to avoid problems when the cluster tries to regenerate the state from the same resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="set-up-the-nfs-share"&gt;Set up the NFS share&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;In my case the required packages to mount NFS shares were already installed in the system, your experience may vary depending on the distribution you are using.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First I had to create the folder where the NFS share will be mounted:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;mkdir&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-p&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;/mnt/k3s-01
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mount the NFS share&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;sudo&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;mount&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;nfs-server.home.arpa:/shares/k3s-01&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;/mnt/k3s-01
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check if the NFS share is mounted correctly by listing the contents of the folder, creating a file and checking the available disk space:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;ls&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;/mnt/k3s-01
k3s-master-01

$&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;df&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-h
Filesystem&lt;span class="w"&gt;      &lt;/span&gt;Size&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;Used&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;Avail&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;Use%&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;Mounted&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;on
...
nfs-server.home.arpa:/shares/k3s-01&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;.8T&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;.1T&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;682G&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="m"&gt;62&lt;/span&gt;%&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;/mnt/k3s-01
...

$&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;touch&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;/mnt/k3s-01/k3s-master-01/test.txt
$&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;ls&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;/mnt/k3s-01/k3s-master-01
test.txt
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this I have the NFS share mounted and ready to be used by the cluster and I can start storing the backups there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-cluster-snapshots"&gt;The cluster snapshots&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thankfully for this k3s &lt;a href="https://docs.k3s.io/datastore/backup-restore"&gt;provides a very straightforward method to create snapshots by either using the &lt;code&gt;k3s etcd-snapshot&lt;/code&gt; command&lt;/a&gt; to create them manually or by setting up a cron job to create them automatically. The cron job is set up by default, so I only had to adjust the schedule and retention to my liking and set up a proper backup location: the NFS share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adjusting the &lt;code&gt;etcd-snapshot-dir&lt;/code&gt; in the k3s configuration file to point to the new location, long with the retention and other options:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# /etc/rancher/k3s/config.yaml&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;etcd-snapshot-retention&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;etcd-snapshot-dir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;/mnt/k3s-01/k3s-master-01/snapshots&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;etcd-snapshot-compress&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After restarting the k3s service the snapshots will be created in the new location and the old ones will be deleted after the retention period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also create a snapshot manually by running the command: &lt;code&gt;k3s etcd-snapshot save&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="longhorn"&gt;Longhorn&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Very easy too! I just followed the &lt;a href="https://longhorn.io/docs/1.6.1/snapshots-and-backups/backup-and-restore/set-backup-target/#set-up-smbcifs-backupstore"&gt;Longhorn documentation on NFS backup store&lt;/a&gt; by going to the Longhorn Web UI and specifying my NFS share as the backup target.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2024/04/21/journey-to-k3s-basic-cluster-backups/longhorn-backup-config-360.jpg" alt="Longhorn backup setup screenshot"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After setting up the backup target I created a backup of the Longhorn volumes and scheduled backups to run every day at 2am with a conservative rentention policy of 3 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes, it was &lt;strong&gt;that&lt;/strong&gt; easy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the backups in place I can now sleep a little better knowing that I can recover from a disaster if needed. The next step is to test the backups and the recovery process to make sure everything is working as expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope I don't need to use this ever, though. :)&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>Importing data manually into a longhorn volume</title><link href="https://fmartingr.com/blog/2024/04/09/import-data-manually-into-a-longhorn-volume/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2024-04-09T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name></name></author><id>urn:uuid:d3359733-7cbe-399b-8b04-34db36b90321</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was in the process of migrating &lt;a href="https://github.com/go-shiori/shiori"&gt;Shiori&lt;/a&gt; from my docker environment to the new &lt;a href="https://blog.josem.dev/2024-04-08-setting-up-a-k3s-cluster-on-raspberry-pi/"&gt;k3s cluster I'm setting up&lt;/a&gt;. Shiori is a bookmarks manager that uses an SQLite database and a folder to store the data from the bookmarks. I didn't want to switch engines just yet since I want to improve SQLite's performance first, so I decided to move the data directly to a longhorn volume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This probably is super simple and vastly known but it wasn't clear for me at first. Posting it here for future reference and for anyone that might find it useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- readmore --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering that I already have the data from the docker volume in a &lt;code&gt;tar.gz&lt;/code&gt; file exported with the correct hierachy the migration process is way simpler than I anticipated. I just need to create the Longhorn volume and the volume claim, create a pod that has access to the volume and pipe the data into the pod to the appropriate location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First create your volume in the way that you prefer. You can apply the YAML directly or use the Longhorn UI to create the volume. I created mine using the UI beforhand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the volume and volume claim (named &lt;code&gt;shiori-data&lt;/code&gt;) created I'm going to create a pod that has access to the volume via the volume claim. I'm going to use the same &lt;code&gt;shiori&lt;/code&gt; image that I'm going to use in the final pod that will use the volume claim since I'm lucky to have the &lt;code&gt;tar&lt;/code&gt; command in there. If you don't have it, you can use a different image that has &lt;code&gt;tar&lt;/code&gt; bundled in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;apiVersion&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;v1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;kind&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;Pod&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;metadata&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;shiori-import-pod&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;namespace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;shiori&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;spec&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;volumes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p p-Indicator"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;      &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;persistentVolumeClaim&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;        &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;claimName&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;shiori-data&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;containers&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p p-Indicator"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;shiori&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;      &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;image&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;ghcr.io/go-shiori/shiori:v1.6.2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;      &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;volumeMounts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;        &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p p-Indicator"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;mountPath&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;/tmp/shiori-data&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;          &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# In my personal case, I need to specify user, group and filesystem group to match the longhorn volume&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# with the docker image specification.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;securityContext&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;runAsUser&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;1000&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;runAsGroup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;1000&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;fsGroup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;1000&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the pod running I can copy the data into the volume by piping it into an &lt;code&gt;exec&lt;/code&gt; call and upacking it with &lt;code&gt;tar&lt;/code&gt; on the fly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;cat&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;shiori_data.tar.gz&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;kubectl&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;exec&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-i&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-n&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;namespace&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;shiori-import-pod&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;--&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;tar&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;xzvf&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-C&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;/tmp/shiori-data/
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: I tried using &lt;code&gt;kubectl cp&lt;/code&gt; before to copy the file into the pod -since internally uses the same approach-, but I had some issues apparently due to different &lt;code&gt;tar&lt;/code&gt; versions on my host machine and the destination pod so I decided to use the pipe approach and it worked. The result should be the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the data copied into the volume I can now delete the import pod and deploy the application using the approrpiate volume claim. In my case I just need to change the &lt;code&gt;mountPath&lt;/code&gt; in the deployment container spec to the correct path where the application expects the data to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know why I expected this to be harder than it really is, but I am happy that I was able to migrate everything in less than an hour.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>Audiobooks can be a great alternative to TV</title><link href="https://fmartingr.com/blog/2024/04/08/audiobooks-can-be-a-great-alternative-to-tv/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2024-04-08T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name></name></author><id>urn:uuid:75db8333-a792-3211-8f0e-eb4d770420af</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We have been doing a sort of experiment lately. My SO had eye surgery a few weeks ago and the first days se barely opened her eyes and even when she could open them blue light took a toll and make her eyes dry and tired really quickly.
Since I still had to work and she had to rest, I suggested her to try out listening to an audiobook. She was a bit skeptical at first, but gave it a try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got her &lt;a href="https://openlibrary.org/works/OL34050635W/Yumi_and_the_Nightmare_Painter?edition="&gt;Yumi and the nightmare painter&lt;/a&gt;; she already read &lt;a href="https://openlibrary.org/works/OL28687656W/Tress_of_the_Emerald_Sea?edition="&gt;Tress of the emerald sea&lt;/a&gt; a few months ago and wanted to read something else from the same author an I got the feeling that this one was good for her too. I had a long plane trip ahead of me at that time too so I tried it out as well, though in my case the book wasn't new to me since I read it last year when it was released.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She loved it, both the book and the experience, and finished it in a couple of days. Even asked for more! Since &lt;em&gt;Yumi and the nightmare painter&lt;/em&gt; is a short book and self-contained, talking to her we decied to try out a longer series together. A friend gave her &lt;a href="https://openlibrary.org/works/OL16807297W/Steelheart_%28The_Reckoners_Book_1%29?edition=steelheart0000sand_g0e1"&gt;Steelheart&lt;/a&gt; for her birthday last year, so we decided to start &lt;em&gt;The Reckoners&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2024/04/08/audiobooks-can-be-a-great-alternative-to-tv/plappa-ios-360.jpeg" alt="Plappa running on my phone playing the last Recokerns book, Calamity"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- readmore --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happened since then? We have been &lt;del&gt;reading&lt;/del&gt; listening to chapters &lt;strong&gt;almost every day&lt;/strong&gt;. I don't remember the day we started, but we have gone through &lt;a href="https://openlibrary.org/works/OL16807297W/Steelheart_%28The_Reckoners_Book_1%29?edition=steelheart0000sand_g0e1"&gt;Steelheart&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://openlibrary.org/books/OL27097630M?edition="&gt;Firefight&lt;/a&gt; and we are 75% through &lt;a href="https://openlibrary.org/books/OL26885980M/Calamity"&gt;Calamity&lt;/a&gt;. That's 35 hours of audiobooks in less than two months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We replaced TV during lunch/dinner with audiobooks, which in our specific case means we can sit down together at the dinning table instead of the couch since not all our furniture aligns with the TV; We also listen to audiobooks while doing chores -making them less boring-, when we sit at the desk doing each his/her own thing and sometimes before going to bed if we are not too tired and can pay attention properly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do we like it? We are spending more time together, we are &lt;em&gt;reading&lt;/em&gt; more, we are enjoying the books we are listening to (would be weird otherwise, yes) with the benefits books have: we are not given everything on a silver plate because we need to use our imagination and that sparks more conversation than just watching TV since we not only discuss what we thing will happen next or how something came to be, but how we imagine the characters, the places, etc. Our heads and past experiences are different, so we have different ideas on how things are in these imaginary worlds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result? We haven't watched TV in almost two months and it doesn't seem that we are going to start watching TV regularly again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Full disclosure:&lt;/strong&gt; While I haven't watched TV with her, I have watched a few episodes of series I'm following on my own, but I have been watching way less TV than usual. A man needs his &lt;a href="https://anilist.co/manga/105398/Na-Honjaman-Level-Up"&gt;Solo leveling&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are enjoying audiobooks a lot and already planning what to listen to next.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>Journey to K3S: Deploying the first service and its requirements</title><link href="https://fmartingr.com/blog/2024/03/25/journey-to-k3s-deploying-the-first-service-and-its-requirements/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2024-03-25T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name></name></author><id>urn:uuid:b2d8d9ae-ebcf-30c7-bc58-7added2de6fa</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have my K3S cluster up and running, and I'm ready to deploy my first service. I'm going to start migrating one of the simplest services I have running in my current docker setup, the RSS reader &lt;a href="https://miniflux.app/"&gt;Miniflux&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm going to use Helm charts through the process since k3s supports Helm out of the box, but for this first service there's also some preparation to do. I'm missing the storage backend, a way to ingress traffic from the internet, a way to manage the certificates and the database. Also, I need to migrate my current data from one database to another, but those are postgresql databases so I guess a simple &lt;code&gt;pg_dump&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;pg_restore&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;psql&lt;/code&gt; commands will do the trick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2024/03/25/journey-to-k3s-deploying-the-first-service-and-its-requirements/k9s-miniflux-running-locally-640.jpg" alt="A screenshot showing the miniflux namespace in my k3s cluster with healthy pods and a request to the internal ingress endpoint showing a 200 status code"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- readmore --&gt;

&lt;h2 id="setting-up-longhorn-for-storage"&gt;Setting up Longhorn for storage&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first thing I need is a storage backend for my services. I'm going to use Longhorn for this, since it's a simple and easy to use solution that works well with k3s. I'm going to install it using Helm, and I'm going to use the default configuration for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# longhorn-helm-chart.yaml&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;apiVersion&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;helm.cattle.io/v1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;kind&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;HelmChart&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;metadata&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;longhorn&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;namespace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;kube-system&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;spec&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;repo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;https://charts.longhorn.io&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;chart&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;longhorn&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;targetNamespace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;longhorn-system&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;createNamespace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;version&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;v1.6.0&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;kubectl&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;apply&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-f&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;longhorn-helm-chart.yaml
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This should generate all required resources for Longhorn to work. In my case I also enabled the ingress for the Longhorn UI to do some set up of the node allocated storage according to my needs and hardware, though I will not cover that in this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# longhorn-ingress.yaml&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;apiVersion&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;networking.k8s.io/v1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;kind&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;Ingress&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;metadata&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;longhorn-ingress&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;namespace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;longhorn-system&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;annotations&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;traefik.ingress.kubernetes.io/router.middlewares&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;longhorn-system-longhorn-auth-middleware@kubernetescrd&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;spec&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;ingressClassName&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;traefik&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;rules&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p p-Indicator"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;host&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;longhorn.k3s-01.home.arpa&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;http&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;      &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;paths&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;      &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p p-Indicator"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;pathType&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;Prefix&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;        &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;path&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;/&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;        &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;backend&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;          &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;service&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;longhorn-frontend&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;              &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;number&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;80&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;kubectl&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;apply&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-f&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;longhorn-ingress.yaml
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this you should be able to access your Longhorn UI at the domain set up in your ingress. In my case it's &lt;code&gt;longhorn.k3s-01.home.arpa&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind that this is a local domain, so you might need to set up a local DNS server or add the domain to your &lt;code&gt;/etc/hosts&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This example is not perfect by any means and if you plan to have this ingress exposed be sure to use a proper certificate and secure your ingress properly with authentication and other security measures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="setting-up-cert-manager-to-manage-certificates"&gt;Setting up cert-manager to manage certificates&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The next step is to set up cert-manager to manage the certificates for my services. I'm going to use Let's Encrypt as my certificate authority and allow cert-manager to generate domains for the external ingresses I'm going to set up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# cert-manager-helm-chart.yaml&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;apiVersion&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;helm.cattle.io/v1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;kind&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;HelmChart&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;metadata&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;cert-manager&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;namespace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;kube-system&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;spec&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;repo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;https://charts.jetstack.io&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;chart&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;cert-manager&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;targetNamespace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;cert-manager&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;createNamespace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;version&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;v1.14.4&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;valuesContent&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p p-Indicator"&gt;|-&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="no"&gt;installCRDs: true&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;kubectl&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;apply&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-f&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;cert-manager-helm-chart.yaml
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to use Let's Encrypt as the certificate authority, I need to set up the issuer for it. I'm going to use the production issuer in this example since the idea is exposing the service to the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# letsencrypt-issuer.yaml&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;apiVersion&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;cert-manager.io/v1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;kind&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;ClusterIssuer&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;metadata&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;letsencrypt-production&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;namespace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;cert-manager&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;spec&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;acme&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;email&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;your@email.com&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;server&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;https://acme-v02.api.letsencrypt.org/directory&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;privateKeySecretRef&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;      &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;letsencrypt-produdction&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;solvers&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p p-Indicator"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;http01&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;        &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;ingress&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;          &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;traefik&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;kubectl&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;apply&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-f&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;letsencrypt-issuer.yaml
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this, I should be able to request certificates for my services using the &lt;code&gt;letsencrypt-production&lt;/code&gt; issuer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="setting-up-the-cloudnative-postgreesql-operator"&gt;Setting up the CloudNative PostgreeSQL Operator&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The chart for Miniflux is capable of deploying a PostgreSQL instance for the service, but I'm going to use the CloudNative PostgreSQL Operator to manage the database for this service (and others) on my own. This is because I want to have the ability to manage the databases separately from the services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Miniflux only supports postgresql so I'm going to use the CloudNative PostgreSQL Operator to manage the database, first let's intall the operator using the Helm chart:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# cloudnative-pg-helm-chart.yaml&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;apiVersion&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;helm.cattle.io/v1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;kind&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;HelmChart&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;metadata&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;cloudnative-pg&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;namespace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;kube-system&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;spec&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;repo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;https://cloudnative-pg.github.io/charts&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;chart&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;cloudnative-pg&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;targetNamespace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;cnpg-system&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;createNamespace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;kubectl&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;apply&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-f&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;cloudnative-pg-helm-chart.yaml
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will install the CloudNative PostgreSQL Operator in the &lt;code&gt;cnpg-system&lt;/code&gt; namespace. I'm going to create a PostgreSQL instance for Miniflux in the &lt;code&gt;miniflux&lt;/code&gt; namespace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# miniflux-db.yaml&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;apiVersion&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;postgresql.cnpg.io/v1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;kind&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;Cluster&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;metadata&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;miniflux-db&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;namespace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;miniflux&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;spec&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;instances&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;storage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;2Gi&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;storageClass&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;longhorn&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;kubectl&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;apply&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-f&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;miniflux-db.yaml
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this a PostgreSQL cluster with two instances and 2Gi of storage will be created in the &lt;code&gt;miniflux&lt;/code&gt; namespace, note that I have specified the &lt;code&gt;longhorn&lt;/code&gt; storage class for the storage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When this is finished a new secret with the connection information for the database called &lt;code&gt;miniflux-db-app&lt;/code&gt; will be created. It will look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;apiVersion&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;v1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;kind&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;Secre&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;type&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;kubernetes.io/basic-auth&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;metadata&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;miniflux-db-app&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;namespace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;miniflux&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# ...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;dbname&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;&amp;lt;base64 encoded data&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;host&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;&amp;lt;base64 encoded data&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;jdbc-uri&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;&amp;lt;base64 encoded data&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;password&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;&amp;lt;base64 encoded data&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;pgpass&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;&amp;lt;base64 encoded data&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;&amp;lt;base64 encoded data&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;uri&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;&amp;lt;base64 encoded data&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;user&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;&amp;lt;base64 encoded data&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;username&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;&amp;lt;base64 encoded data&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are going to reference this secret directly in the Miniflux deployment below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="deploying-miniflux"&gt;Deploying Miniflux&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now that we have all the requirements set up, we can deploy Miniflux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm going to use &lt;a href="https://artifacthub.io/packages/helm/gabe565/miniflux"&gt;gabe565's miniflux helm chart&lt;/a&gt; for this, since they are simple and easy to use. I tried the &lt;a href="https://artifacthub.io/packages/helm/truecharts/miniflux"&gt;TrueCharts&lt;/a&gt; chart but I couldn't get it to work properly, since they only support amd64 and I'm running on arm64, though a few tweaks here and there &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; make it work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# miniflux-helm-chart.yaml&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;apiVersion&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;helm.cattle.io/v1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;kind&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;HelmChart&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;metadata&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;miniflux&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;namespace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;kube-system&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;spec&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;repo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;https://charts.gabe565.com&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;chart&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;miniflux&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;targetNamespace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;miniflux&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;createNamespace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;version&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;0.8.1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;valuesContent&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p p-Indicator"&gt;|-&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="no"&gt;image:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;      &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="no"&gt;tag: 2.1.1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="no"&gt;env:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;      &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="no"&gt;CREATE_ADMIN: &amp;quot;0&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;      &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="no"&gt;DATABASE_URL:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;        &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="no"&gt;secretKeyRef:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;          &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="no"&gt;name: miniflux-db-app&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;          &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="no"&gt;key: uri&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="no"&gt;postgresql:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;      &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="no"&gt;enabled: false&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;In order to customize Miniflux check out their &lt;a href="https://miniflux.app/docs/configuration.html"&gt;configuration&lt;/a&gt; documentation and set the appropriate values in the &lt;code&gt;env&lt;/code&gt; section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;kubectl&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;apply&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-f&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;miniflux-helm-chart.yaml
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm using &lt;code&gt;CREATE_ADMIN: "0"&lt;/code&gt; to avoid creating an admin user for Miniflux, since I already have one in my current database after I migrated it. If you want to create an admin user you can set this to &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt; and set the &lt;code&gt;ADMIN_USERNAME&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;ADMIN_PASSWORD&lt;/code&gt; values in the &lt;code&gt;env&lt;/code&gt; section. See the &lt;a href="https://artifacthub.io/packages/helm/gabe565/miniflux"&gt;chart documentation&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will create a Miniflux deployment in the &lt;code&gt;miniflux&lt;/code&gt; namespace, using the &lt;code&gt;miniflux-db-app&lt;/code&gt; database secret for the database connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wait until everything is ready in the &lt;code&gt;miniflux&lt;/code&gt; namespace:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;kubectl&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;get&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;pods&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-n&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;miniflux
NAME&lt;span class="w"&gt;                        &lt;/span&gt;READY&lt;span class="w"&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;STATUS
miniflux-678b9c8ff5-7dbj5&lt;span class="w"&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;/1&lt;span class="w"&gt;     &lt;/span&gt;Running
miniflux-db-1&lt;span class="w"&gt;               &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;/1&lt;span class="w"&gt;     &lt;/span&gt;Running
miniflux-db-2&lt;span class="w"&gt;               &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;/1&lt;span class="w"&gt;     &lt;/span&gt;Running

$&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;kubectl&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;logs&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-n&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;miniflux&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;miniflux-678b9c8ff5-7dbj5
&lt;span class="nv"&gt;time&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="m"&gt;2024&lt;/span&gt;-03-24T23:00:42.487+01:00&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;level&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;INFO&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;msg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Starting HTTP server&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;listen_address&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;.0.0.0:8080
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id="setting-up-an-external-ingress"&gt;Setting up an external ingress&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm not going to cover the networking setup for this but your cluster should be able to route traffic from the internet to the ingress controller (the master nodes). In my case I'm using a zero-trust approach with Tailscale to avoid exposing my homelab directly to the internet but there are a number of ways to do this, pick the one that suits you best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting up an ingress for the service that supports SSL is easy with cert-manager and Traefik, we only need to create an &lt;code&gt;Ingress&lt;/code&gt; resource in the &lt;code&gt;miniflux&lt;/code&gt; namespace with the appropiate configuration and annotations and cert-manager will take care of the rest:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# miniflux-ingress.yaml&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;apiVersion&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;networking.k8s.io/v1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;kind&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;Ingress&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;metadata&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;miniflux-external&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;namespace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;miniflux&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;annotations&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;cert-manager.io/cluster-issuer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;letsencrypt-production&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;spec&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;ingressClassName&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;traefik&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;rules&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p p-Indicator"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;host&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;miniflux.fmartingr.com&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;http&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;      &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;paths&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;      &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p p-Indicator"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;pathType&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;Prefix&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;        &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;path&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;/&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;        &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;backend&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;          &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;service&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;miniflux&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;            &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;port&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;              &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;number&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;8080&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;tls&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p p-Indicator"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;secretName&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;miniflux-fmartingr-com-tls&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;      &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;hosts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;      &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p p-Indicator"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;miniflux.fmartingr.com&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;kubectl&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;apply&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-f&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;miniflux-ingress.yaml
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will create an ingress for Miniflux in the &lt;code&gt;miniflux&lt;/code&gt; namespace and cert-manager will take care of the certificate generation and renewal using the &lt;code&gt;letsencrypt-production&lt;/code&gt; issuer as specified in the &lt;code&gt;annotations&lt;/code&gt; attribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few minutes you should be able to access Miniflux at the domain set up in the &lt;code&gt;host&lt;/code&gt; field:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ curl -I https://miniflux.fmartingr.com
HTTP/2 200
server: traefik
...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that's it! You should have Miniflux up and running in your k3s cluster with all the requirements set up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't recommend &lt;a href="https://miniflux.app"&gt;Miniflux&lt;/a&gt; enough, it's a great RSS reader that is simple to use and has a great UI. It probably is the first service I deployed in my homelab and I'm happy to have it running in my k3s cluster now, years later.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>Journey to K3S: Basic cluster setup</title><link href="https://fmartingr.com/blog/2024/03/14/journey-to-k3s-basic-cluster-setup/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2024-03-14T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name></name></author><id>urn:uuid:aca280ee-181f-3839-bd3b-0e6dea8615ee</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've finally started to play with K3S, a lightweight Kubernetes distribution. I have been reading about it for a while and I'm excited to see how it performs in my home lab. My services have been running in an Intel NUC running Docker container for some years now, but the plan is to migrate them to a k3s cluster of three NanoPC-T6 boards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was looking for a small form-factor and low power consumption solution, and the NanoPC-T6 seems to fit the bill. I know I'm going to stumble upon some limitations but I'm eager to see how it goes and the problems I find along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My requirements are very simple: I want to run a small cluster with a few services, and I want to be able to access them from the internet and from my home. My current setup relies on Tailscale for VPN and Ingress for the services, so I'm going to try and replicate that in this new setup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2024/03/14/journey-to-k3s-basic-cluster-setup/nanopc-cluster-360.jpeg" alt="Picture of three nanopc-t6 computers on top of each other running k3s"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- readmore --&gt;

&lt;h2 id="installing-dietpi-on-the-nanopc-t6"&gt;Installing DietPi on the NanoPC-T6&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm completely new to &lt;a href="https://dietpi.com"&gt;DietPi&lt;/a&gt;, but nothing that FriendlyElec offered seemed to fit my needs. I'm not a fan of the pre-installed software and I wanted to start from scratch. I tried to find compatible OSs around and there weren't many, but DietPi seemed to be a good fit and it's actively maintained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first I tried to run from an SD Card and try and copy the data manually, but I found out that the NanoPC-T6 has an eMMC slot, so I decided to go with that. I flashed FriendlyWRT into the SD Card, booted it and used their tools to flash DietPi into the eMMC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;For this to work properly under my home network setup I had to physically connect a computer and a keyboard to the boards and disable the firewall service using: &lt;code&gt;service firewall stop&lt;/code&gt;. I believe this happened because the boards live in a different VLAN/subnet in my local network since I connect new devices to a different VLAN for security reasons. With that disabled I could access the boards from my computer and continue the setup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2024/03/14/journey-to-k3s-basic-cluster-setup/friendlywrt-emmc-tools-360.jpg" alt="Flashing DietPi into the NanoPC-T6 using FriendlyWRT&amp;#39;s web interface"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="setting-up-the-os"&gt;Setting up the OS&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first thing once you SSH to the boards is to change the default and global software passwords. Once the setup assistant was over I setup a new SSH key and disabled the password login.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before installing K3s I wanted to make sure the OS was up to date and had the necessary tools to run the cluster. I used the &lt;code&gt;dietpi-software&lt;/code&gt; tool to be sure that some convenience utilities like &lt;code&gt;vim&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;curl&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; where present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also set up the hostname by using the &lt;code&gt;dietpi-config&lt;/code&gt; tool to &lt;code&gt;k3s-master-03&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;k3s-master-02&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;k3s-master-03&lt;/code&gt; for the three boards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And installed &lt;code&gt;open-iscsi&lt;/code&gt; to be prepared in the case I end up setting up &lt;a href="https://longhorn.io/"&gt;Longhorn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="setting-up-the-network"&gt;Setting up the network&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm using Tailscale to connect the boards to my home network and to the internet. I installed &lt;a href="https://tailscale.com"&gt;Tailscale&lt;/a&gt; using &lt;code&gt;dietpi-software&lt;/code&gt; and link the device to my account using &lt;code&gt;tailscale up&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also set up the static IP address for the boards using my home router. I'm using a custom &lt;a href="https://www.pfsense.org/"&gt;pfsense&lt;/a&gt; router and I set up the IP address for the boards using the MAC address of the boards on the VLAN they are going to reside in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="installing-k3s"&gt;Installing K3S&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I followed the &lt;a href="https://docs.k3s.io/datastore/ha-embedded"&gt;official documentation&lt;/a&gt; to create an embedded etcd highly available cluster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm not a fan of the &lt;code&gt;curl ... | sh&lt;/code&gt; installation methods around, but this is the official way to install K3S and I'm going to follow it for convenience. &lt;strong&gt;Always check the script before running it.&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I created the first node using the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;curl&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-sfL&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;https://get.k3s.io&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;K3S_TOKEN&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;token&amp;gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;sh&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-s&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;server&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;--cluster-init
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used the &lt;code&gt;K3S_TOKEN&lt;/code&gt; environment variable to set the token for the cluster that I will need to join the other two nodes to the cluster. Since this is the first node of the cluster I had to provide the &lt;code&gt;--cluster-init&lt;/code&gt; flag to initialize the cluster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I joined the other two nodes to the cluster using the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;curl&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-sfL&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;https://get.k3s.io&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;K3S_TOKEN&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;token&amp;gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;sh&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-s&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;server&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;--server&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;https://&amp;lt;internal&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;ip&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;of&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;the&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;first&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;node&amp;gt;:6443
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Done! I have a three node K3S cluster running in my home lab. Is &lt;strong&gt;that&lt;/strong&gt; simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2024/03/14/journey-to-k3s-basic-cluster-setup/kubectl-nodes-ready-360.jpg" alt="Output of kubectl get nodes showing three ready nodes"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="checking-that-it-works"&gt;Checking that it works&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm going to deploy a simple service to check that the cluster is working properly. I'm going to use the &lt;code&gt;nginx&lt;/code&gt; image and expose it using an Ingress:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Create the &lt;code&gt;hello-world&lt;/code&gt; namespace:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;kubectl&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;create&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;namespace&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;hello-world
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Create a simple index file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Hello, world!&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;index.html
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Create a &lt;code&gt;ConfigMap&lt;/code&gt; with the index file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;kubectl&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;create&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;configmap&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;hello-world-index-html&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;--from-file&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;index.html&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-n&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;hello-world
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Create a deployment using the &lt;code&gt;nginx&lt;/code&gt; image and the config map we just created:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;kubectl&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;apply&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-f&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;EOF&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt; apiVersion: apps/v1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt; kind: Deployment&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt; metadata:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;     name: hello-world-nginx&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;     namespace: hello-world&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt; spec:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;     selector:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;         matchLabels:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;         app: hello-world&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;     replicas: 3&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;     template:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;         metadata:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;         labels:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;             app: hello-world&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;         spec:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;         containers:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;         - name: nginx&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;             image: nginx&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;             ports:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;             - containerPort: 80&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;             volumeMounts:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;             - name: hello-world-volume&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;             mountPath: /usr/share/nginx/html&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;         volumes:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;         - name: hello-world-volume&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;             configMap:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;             name: hello-world-index-html&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt; EOF&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Create the service to expose the deployment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;kubectl&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;apply&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-f&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;EOF&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt; apiVersion: v1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt; kind: Service&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt; metadata:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;     name: hello-world&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;     namespace: hello-world&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt; spec:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;     ports:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;         - port: 80&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;         protocol: TCP&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;     selector:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;         app:  hello-world&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt; EOF&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Create the Ingress to expose the service to the internet:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;kubectl&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;apply&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-f&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;EOF&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt; apiVersion: networking.k8s.io/v1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt; kind: Ingress&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt; metadata:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;     name: hello-world&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;     namespace: hello-world&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt; spec:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;     ingressClassName: &amp;quot;traefik&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;     rules:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;     - host: hello-world.fmartingr.dev&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;       http:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;         paths:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;         - path: /&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;             pathType: Prefix&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;             backend:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;             service:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;                 name: hello-world&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;                 port:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt;                 number: 80&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s"&gt; EOF&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Done! I can access the service from my local network using the &lt;code&gt;hello-world.fmartingr.dev&lt;/code&gt; domain:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2024/03/14/journey-to-k3s-basic-cluster-setup/curl-ingress-ready-360.jpg" alt="A curl command to one of the nodes checking ingress connectivity"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's it! I have a cluster running and I can start playing with it. There's a lot more to be done and progress will be slow since I'm doing this in my free time to dogfood kubernetes at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will follow up with updates once I make more progress, see you on the next one.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>Create an audiobook file from several mp3 files using ffmpeg</title><link href="https://fmartingr.com/blog/2024/03/12/create-an-audiobook-file-from-several-mp3-files-using-ffmpeg/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2024-03-12T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name></name></author><id>urn:uuid:a52b1299-22bd-3c40-8218-14b02f1c79b0</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Due to some recent traveling I have started to listen to audiobooks. I love reading but some times my eyes are just too tired to go with it but I'm not sleepy at all or maybe I just wanted the convenience to lay down but still &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Short story, I bought some from a known distributor but I'm a fan of data preservation and actually owning what I pay for. I found an application in Github that allowed me to download the files that composed the audiobook in split mp3 files, but that didn't do. I wanted a single file with correct metadata, so I got my hands dirty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2024/03/12/create-an-audiobook-file-from-several-mp3-files-using-ffmpeg/book_player_screenshot-360.jpeg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- readmore --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming you have the mp3 laying around in a folder, we need to generate or find three more things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;files.txt&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: A list of the MP3 files in the order we are going to combine them, in a plain text file with the format &lt;code&gt;file '&amp;lt;filename&amp;gt;'&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can use a simple bash command to generate the file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;find&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;.&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-type&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;f&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-name&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;*mp3&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-exec&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;printf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;file &amp;#39;%s&amp;#39;\n&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;{}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;sed&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;s|\.\/||g&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;files.txt
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;metadata.txt&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: A metadata file to be used with the bundled file that contain basic information of the audiobook (title, author, narrator, ...) along with chapter information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example looks like this, documentation can be found &lt;a href="https://ffmpeg.org/ffmpeg-formats.html#Metadata-1"&gt;in the ffmpeg documentation&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;;FFMETADATA1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;Book name&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;artist&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;Book author(s)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;composer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;Book narrator(s)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;publisher&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;Book publisher&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;date&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;Book date of publication&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;[CHAPTER]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;TIMEBASE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;1/1000&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;START&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# 0:00:00&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;END&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;60000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# 0:01:00&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;Intro&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Chapter title&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Repeat the [CHAPTER] block for all chapters&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;cover.jpg&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: The artwork of the audiobook. The files I have been using (downloaded from the store) are 353x353@72dpi. I'm unsure if that's by definition, but at least be sure to use squared images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all the files in place, we can use &lt;code&gt;ffmpeg&lt;/code&gt; to do the conversion. I have followed a multi step approach to make sure I can review the process and fix any issues that may arise. Pretty sure this can be simplified somehow but I'm not a &lt;code&gt;ffmpeg&lt;/code&gt; expert and I have spent too much time on this already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Concatenate the files into a single &lt;code&gt;mp3&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;ffmpeg&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-f&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;concat&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-i&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;files.txt&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-c&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;copy&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;build_01_concat.mp3
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;-f concat&lt;/code&gt;: Use the &lt;code&gt;concat&lt;/code&gt; format, meaning we are going to concatenate files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;-i files.txt&lt;/code&gt;: The file with the list of files to concatenate as input to ffmpeg.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;-c copy&lt;/code&gt;: The stream copy codec for each stream, meaning we are not going to re-encode the files, just copy them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;build_01_concat.mp3&lt;/code&gt;: The output file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add the cover to the file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;ffmpeg&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-i&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;build_01_concat.mp3&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-i&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;cover.jpg&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-c&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;copy&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-map&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-map&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;build_02_cover.mp3
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;-i build_01_concat.mp3&lt;/code&gt;: The file created in the above step to be used as input to ffmpeg.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;-i cover.jpg&lt;/code&gt;: The cover image to be added to the file as second input to ffmpeg.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;-c copy&lt;/code&gt;: The stream copy codec for each stream, meaning we are not going to re-encode the files, just copy them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;-map 0 -map 1&lt;/code&gt;: Maps the streams from the input files to the output file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;build_02_cover.mp3&lt;/code&gt;: The output file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Convert the &lt;code&gt;mp3&lt;/code&gt; file to &lt;code&gt;m4a&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;ffmpeg&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-i&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;build_02_cover.mp3&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-c:v&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;copy&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;build_03_m4a.m4a
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;-i build_02_cover.mp3&lt;/code&gt;: The file created in the above step to be used as input to ffmpeg.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;-c:v copy&lt;/code&gt;: The video codec to be used for the output file, meaning we are not going to re-encode the file, just copy it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;build_03_m4a.m4a&lt;/code&gt;: The output file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add the metadata to the &lt;code&gt;m4a&lt;/code&gt; file and convert it to &lt;code&gt;m4b&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;ffmpeg&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-i&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;build_03_m4a.m4a&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-i&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;metadata.txt&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-map&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-map_metadata&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;-c&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;copy&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;book.m4b
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;-i build_03_m4a.m4a&lt;/code&gt;: The file created in the above step to be used as input to ffmpeg.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;-i metadata.txt&lt;/code&gt;: The metadata file to be used as second input to ffmpeg.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;-map 0 -map_metadata 1&lt;/code&gt;: Maps the streams from the input files to the output file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;-c copy&lt;/code&gt;: The stream copy codec for each stream, meaning we are not going to re-encode the files, just copy them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;book.m4b&lt;/code&gt;: The final output file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clean up the files we created in the process that we don't need anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;rm&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;build_*&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;files.txt
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's it! You should have a &lt;code&gt;m4b&lt;/code&gt; file with the audiobook ready to be imported to your favorite audiobook player. I have tested this process with a couple of books and it worked like a charm. I hope it helps you too.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>FOSDEM 2024</title><link href="https://fmartingr.com/blog/2024/02/26/fosdem-2024/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2024-02-26T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name></name></author><id>urn:uuid:1ad072d2-372c-3a10-9747-96261c90e4e6</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2024/02/26/fosdem-2024/fosdem-2024-360.jpeg" alt="FOSDEM 2024 Opening Keynote"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First weekend of February was, as usual, the FOSDEM conference in Belgium, and I could not miss it. I started attending a few years back, and since then I have tried going if my schedule allowed it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a super brief summary of my experience during the event on the two days I was there, though this year I left early on Sunday before the conference properly finished so Sunday was a bit more scarce. A lot of unattended talks from the agenda too, I have a &lt;strong&gt;huge&lt;/strong&gt; backlog of videos to watch now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- readmore --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual I met with friends and old colleagues and the event in general was a blast. I came back with recharged batteries to dedicate to my open source projects and to revive this blog. I didn't have much spare time to dedicate to anything since then, but I will try to do a bit of daily grind to meet some goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="saturday"&gt;Saturday&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the best day for me because you come fresh and with a lot of motivation (unless you came back late from Delirium Cafe that night!) and eager to get things rolling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a crappy breakfast (because there was no coffeeshop open nearby our place but Starbucks) we went to the conference and the first thing to do, donate! I got a hoodie a two t-shirts. I think is only natural to donate &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; to an event that is free to attend for everyone, and very well organized on top of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I may be biased on that last statement, since this is the only conference I attend. Years ago I attended more (mostly local conferences in Spain) but now this is the one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the &lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-3023-welcome-to-fosdem-2024/"&gt;Welcome to FOSDEM 2024&lt;/a&gt; starting keynote, I made myself strong on the Go track since it was the one that interested me the most and a colleague was giving a talk as well, and I attended a few in that track (with a stop to have lunch, of course).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-1681-the-state-of-go/"&gt;The state of Go&lt;/a&gt;: A regular for the past years, an update of what interesting changes happened (or are about to happen) with Go since last FOSDEM. In this case I already new most of them but made notes to review &lt;code&gt;yield&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;RangeFunc&lt;/code&gt; which I didn't kew were coming to the language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-1704-the-secret-life-of-a-goroutine/"&gt;The secret life of a goroutine&lt;/a&gt;: An interesting talk talking about how goroutines work from the point of view of a &lt;em&gt;necromancer&lt;/em&gt;. The content was good but rushed, since the speaker only had 25m minutes and it had to prepare the audience and then explain the concepts, but going deeper or have a better understanding is good homework for the audience (us) to do afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-1813-you-re-already-running-my-code-in-production-my-simple-journey-to-becoming-a-go-contributor-/"&gt;You're already running my code in production: My simple journey to becoming a Go contributor.&lt;/a&gt;: The humble story of how a bug became a Go contribution and what were the steps required to arrive to that, showing that anyone can aim to make a contribution to the Go source code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-2000-maintaining-go-as-a-day-job-a-year-later/"&gt;Maintaining Go as a day job - a year later&lt;/a&gt;: A very descriptive and fun talk about the pros and cons of maintaining open source software from his point of view as a maintainer of the cryptography library, as well as other contractors, showing that working in open source full time is possible, just not what you might expect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-1884-how-we-almost-secured-our-projects-by-writing-more-tests/"&gt;How we almost secured our projects by writing more tests&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-1868-dependency-injection-a-different-way-to-structure-a-project/"&gt;Dependency injection: a different way to structure a project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-1853-putting-an-end-to-makefiles-in-go-projects-with-goreleaser/"&gt;Putting an end to Makefiles in go projects with GoReleaser&lt;/a&gt;: Already knew that Goreleaser was awesome, but his statement was bold enough to catch my interest. In the end it just showed up basic concepts of Goreleaser, and I still love my Makefiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-2621-low-code-graphical-apps-with-go-top-to-bottom-/"&gt;Low code graphical apps with Go top to bottom!&lt;/a&gt;: A talk about &lt;a href="https://fyne.io/"&gt;fyne&lt;/a&gt; and the new (or at least new to me) &lt;a href="https://github.com/fyne-io/defyne"&gt;fyne GUI editor "defyne"&lt;/a&gt;, showing up how you can build interfaces directly from a graphical interface and it automatically generates some JSON definitions and Go code to go with your app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-1886-creating-a-multiplayer-game-in-go-from-zero/"&gt;Creating a multiplayer game in Go, from zero&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-2562-smartwatch-firmware-in-go-on-tinygo-small-displays-and-building-a-delightful-developer-experience/"&gt;Smartwatch firmware... in Go? On TinyGo, small displays, and building a delightful developer experience&lt;/a&gt;:Content was super interesting and fun, though the speaker was clearly nervous, it was amazing how a super small firmware with go for the pine time was built, and even with just basic features I saw on the fediverse that the battery lasted for more than a month!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-2270-go-without-wires-strikes-back/"&gt;Go Without Wires Strikes Back&lt;/a&gt;: It was a bit of a lie, since there were wires involved, but -as expected- it didn't disappoint, and he managed to fly a drone over the crowd, &lt;strong&gt;again&lt;/strong&gt;. TinyGo looks awesome, if I just had some project that could build with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And with that, we left for the day to have dinner. The venue of choice was the &lt;a href="https://www.brewdog.com/eu_en/brewdog-brussels"&gt;Brew Dog&lt;/a&gt; since there were some events happening in there the day before, we choose to go there for dinner and some drinks and we met with some people from FOSDEM as well, as there were more meetups happening on Saturday too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, another mandatory visit to Delirium Cafe, and the day was over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sunday"&gt;Sunday&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I attended way less talks than anticipated because:
1) Sunday usually is social day, that means I usually find old colleagues and friends around so I stop to chat, grab something to drink, etc.
2) This year I left on Sunday so I had to skip some of the afternoon talks.
3) I also missed some morning talks because the taxi that had to pick me up bluntly ignored me and went its way, so I arrived more than an hour late to the venue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When life give you lemons, you made lemonade. I took advantage of the situation and sat down around with my laptop to clean Github notifications that pile up week after week until I cleaned them, I wanted to release &lt;a href="https://github.com/go-shiori/shiori"&gt;shiori&lt;/a&gt; 1.6.0 during FOSDEM but an unfortunate Windows bug had other plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the talks I attended that day:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-1652--new-workflow-orchestrator-in-town-apache-airflow-2-x-/"&gt;New Workflow Orchestrator in town: "Apache Airflow 2.x"&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-1651-data-workflows-translating-dbt-to-apache-airflow/"&gt;Data workflows: translating dbt to Apache Airflow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-2326-a-slow-migration-from-django-templates-to-vue-graphql/"&gt;A slow migration from Django templates to Vue+GraphQL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-2194-chaos-engineering-in-action-enhancing-resilience-in-strimzi/"&gt;Chaos Engineering in Action: Enhancing Resilience in Strimzi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-3423-version-control-post-git/"&gt;Version control post-Git&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And from there, to the airport, and home! See you next year FOSDEM!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-ones-i-missed"&gt;The ones I missed&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This are all the talks that I missed because of the problems I had, conflicting events or because I didn't make it in time/room was full, in no particular order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-2850-where-have-the-women-of-tech-history-gone-/"&gt;Where have the women of tech history gone?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-2161-diy-private-container-registry/"&gt;DIY Private Container Registry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-3743-open-food-facts-learning-and-using-perl-in-2024-to-transform-the-food-system-/"&gt;Open Food Facts: Learning and using Perl in 2024 to transform the food system !&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-3740-observations-on-a-dnssec-incident-the-russian-tld/"&gt;Observations on a DNSSEC incident: the russian TLD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-2671-a-simple-caching-service-for-your-ci/"&gt;A simple caching service for your CI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-2952-the-api-landscape-mapping-the-2000-api-and-opensource-tooling-for-developers/"&gt;The API Landscape : mapping the 2000+ API and opensource tooling for Developers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-1927-effortless-bug-hunting-with-differential-fuzzing/"&gt;Effortless Bug Hunting with Differential Fuzzing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-3656-cost-effective-ai-processing-with-open-source-infrastructure/"&gt;Cost-Effective AI Processing with Open Source Infrastructure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-3060-what-s-new-in-containerd-2-0-/"&gt;What's new in Containerd 2.0!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-3264-an-open-source-open-hardware-offline-finding-system/"&gt;An open-source, open-hardware offline finding system&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-3187-vscode-container-wasm-an-extension-of-vscode-on-browser-for-running-containers-within-your-browser/"&gt;vscode-container-wasm: An Extension of VSCode on Browser for Running Containers Within Your Browser&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-2146-how-do-you-write-an-emulator-anyway-/"&gt;How do you write an emulator anyway ?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-1726-panda3ds-climbing-the-tree-of-3ds-emulation/"&gt;Panda3DS: Climbing the tree of 3DS emulation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-2826-breathing-life-into-legacy-an-open-source-emulator-of-legacy-apple-devices/"&gt;Breathing Life into Legacy: An Open-Source Emulator of Legacy Apple Devices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-2247-confedss-concolic-execution-and-the-puzzling-practice-of-peripheral-emulation/"&gt;CONFEDSS: Concolic execution and the puzzling practice of peripheral emulation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-1762-arm64ec-microsoft-s-emulation-frankenstein/"&gt;Arm64EC: Microsoft's emulation Frankenstein&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-2255-yet-another-event-sourcing-library/"&gt;Yet another event sourcing library&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-2560-self-hosting-and-autonomy-using-guix-forge/"&gt;Self-hosting and autonomy using guix-forge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-2046-do-you-know-yaml-/"&gt;Do you know YAML?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-3592-welcome-to-retrocomputing-devroom/"&gt;Welcome to Retrocomputing Devroom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-3154-project-websites-that-don-t-suck/"&gt;Project websites that don't suck&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-2043-foss-for-docs/"&gt;FOSS for DOCS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-1776-journey-to-an-open-source-contribution/"&gt;Journey to an open source contribution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-1771-gameboy-advance-hacking-for-retrogamers/"&gt;Gameboy Advance hacking for retrogamers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-3629-gotta-catch-em-all-raspberry-pi-and-java-pokemon-training/"&gt;Gotta Catch Em All! Raspberry Pi and Java Pokemon Training&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-1718-a-game-boy-and-his-cellphone/"&gt;A Game Boy and his cellphone&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-3342-the-wonderful-life-of-a-sql-query-in-a-streaming-database/"&gt;The wonderful life of a SQL query in a streaming database&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-3472-switching-the-fosdem-conference-management-system-to-pretalx/"&gt;Switching the FOSDEM conference management system to pretalx&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2024/schedule/event/fosdem-2024-2802-s2s-peertube-instance-dedicated-to-sign-language/"&gt;S2S: PeerTube instance dedicated to Sign Language&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;... and probably others&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="worth-mentioning"&gt;Worth mentioning&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h3 id="cookies-from-firefox"&gt;Cookies from Firefox!&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was a small stand that gave free cookies courtesy of Firefox. Do you accept cookies?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2024/02/26/fosdem-2024/cookies-from-firefox-640.jpeg" alt="Firefox food truck giving free cookies to FOSDEM atendees"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="macbook-pro-m2-battery-life"&gt;MacBook Pro M2 battery life&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;I removed my laptop from current early Friday morning, when I arrived back home Sunday night my laptop still had 19% battery left, after use it to take notes, watch videos, develop, having &lt;a href="https://orbstack.dev/"&gt;orbstack&lt;/a&gt; running in the background... In terms of battery I haven't seen anything better.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>My defaults at the end of 2023</title><link href="https://fmartingr.com/blog/2023/12/31/my-defaults-at-the-end-of-2023/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2023-12-31T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name></name></author><id>urn:uuid:55d9ce6b-6259-3e9b-a05f-0060cedfbb87</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm too joining this trend, since it seems like a good idea to keep track of the tools I use, others may discover new ones as I have done in people lists, and it's a good way to see how my preferences change over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's my list for this year:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Category&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Tools/Platforms&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Operating System&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.apple.com/macos/"&gt;MacOS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Launcher&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.alfredapp.com/"&gt;Alfred&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Mobile OS&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.apple.com/iphone/"&gt;iPhone&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Mail Client&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.fastmail.com/"&gt;Fastmail Web&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Notes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.notion.so/"&gt;Notion&lt;/a&gt; (personal) &amp;amp; &lt;a href="https://obsidian.md/"&gt;Obsidian&lt;/a&gt; (personal/work)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Photo Management&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://photos.google.com/"&gt;Google Photos&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href="https://www.icloud.com/photos/"&gt;iCloud Photos&lt;/a&gt; / Local NAS (A mess)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Calendar&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://flexibits.com/fantastical"&gt;Fantastical&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Contacts&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.fastmail.com/"&gt;Fastmail&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; File Storage&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.synology.com/en-us/dsm/feature/drive"&gt;SynologyDrive&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href="https://syncthing.net/"&gt;Syncthing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Browser&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://arc.net/"&gt;Arc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Search Engine&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://kagi.com"&gt;Kagi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Bookmarks&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/go-shiori/shiori"&gt;Shiori&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Read It Later&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/go-shiori/shiori"&gt;Shiori&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; RSS Reader&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://miniflux.app/"&gt;Miniflux&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Task Management&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://todoist.com/"&gt;Todoist&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Shopping Lists&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://todoist.com/"&gt;Todoist&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Social Media&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://joinmastodon.org/"&gt;Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Chat&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://telegram.org/"&gt;Telegram&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://element.io/"&gt;Element&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://support.apple.com/explore/messages"&gt;iMessage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Finances&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://actualbudget.com/"&gt;Actual&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Music&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://music.apple.com/"&gt;Apple Music&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href="https://bandcamp.com/"&gt;Bandcamp&lt;/a&gt; / Local NAS&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Podcasts&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.apple.com/podcasts/"&gt;Apple Podcasts&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href="https://www.ivoox.com/"&gt;iVoox&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Password Management&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://1password.com/"&gt;1Password&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; IDE and Code Editor&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://code.visualstudio.com/"&gt;Visual Studio Code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; VPN&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://tailscale.com/"&gt;Tailscale&lt;/a&gt; , &lt;a href="https://www.wireguard.com/"&gt;WireGuard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; Home automation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.home-assistant.io/"&gt;Home Assistant&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>I just read The Sunlit Man</title><link href="https://fmartingr.com/blog/2023/10/27/i-just-read-the-sunlit-man/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2023-10-27T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name></name></author><id>urn:uuid:88cb5e23-e907-389f-8911-e394de64ab85</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2023/10/27/i-just-read-the-sunlit-man/el-hombre-iluminado-cover-360.jpg" alt="Cover for the Spanish version of The Sunlit Man"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Name&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;The Sunlit Man&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Author&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Brandon Sanderson&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Pages&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;544 (Spanish physical edition)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Rating&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;4 (out of 6)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Recommended&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;For Sanderson fans and fantasy/sci-fi lovers, yes.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;The last &lt;em&gt;Secret Novel&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;Brandon Sanderson&lt;/em&gt;, titled &lt;em&gt;The Sunlit Man&lt;/em&gt; (or &lt;em&gt;El hombre iluminado&lt;/em&gt; in Spanish, the version I read). This is the most Cosmere focused novel of the four, with a lot of references to &lt;em&gt;The Stormlight Archives&lt;/em&gt; series; or at least I guess so, since I haven't read any books from that series yet, though some names feel familiar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've enjoyed it, just not as much as the others to be honest. I liked the environment a lot and the idea of &lt;span class="spoiler"&gt;a planet that can kill you easily&lt;/span&gt; and what that means for the population of the planet, their livelihood, their interactions, ... In the end is a Space Opera &lt;em&gt;ala Sanderson&lt;/em&gt;, and I don't know if I just got spoiled with &lt;em&gt;Tress of the Emerald Sea&lt;/em&gt; (my favorite of the three) that I just wanted something as different. and this one being the most similar to the novels I already read from Sanderson just made it a little worse for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even with that, I recommend fantasy/sci-fi lovers a read; it's just around 500 pages of non-stop movement, you get to the heart of the story pretty quickly and from there is just non-stop movement until you get to the outcome in the final two-three chapters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And with this, the &lt;a href="https://www.dragonsteelbooks.com/collections/the-year-of-sanderson"&gt;year of Sanderson&lt;/a&gt; is over.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>Using ssh_config Match to connect to a host using multiple IP or Hostnames</title><link href="https://fmartingr.com/blog/2022/08/12/using-ssh-config-match-to-connect-to-a-host-using-multiple-ip-or-hostnames/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2022-08-12T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name></name></author><id>urn:uuid:cb258fe5-1432-307e-8e67-7e430b4a8427</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My main computer is a MacBook Pro from 2017, but I have some servers laying around and one other laptop connected at home
with ArchLinux installed that I use mainly for development. I connect to it remotely either directly using a
SSH/Mosh + Tmux + Emacs/Vim combination, or using the pretty convenient VSCode Remote Extensions when I'm not feeling
much of a &lt;em&gt;hacker&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thing is, I may access this computer either from my home network directly if I'm at home or via a SDN if I am not (at the office,
coffeeshop, visiting family, etc).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My approach was to setup the hosts directly on my &lt;code&gt;~/.ssh/ssh_config&lt;/code&gt; as you would with different machines:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# .ssh/config&lt;/span&gt;
Host&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;laptop.lan
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;HostName&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="m"&gt;192&lt;/span&gt;.168.1.2&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Internal network IP&lt;/span&gt;

Host&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;laptop.sdn
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;Hostname&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="m"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;.0.0.2&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# SDN IP&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That way, I would connect to each one of them depending on the situation. Using tmux and ssh is not that much of a problem
since I could just detach from home, go away, then connect via SDN an everything would be there (though I had to remember
which alias to use instead of just &lt;code&gt;ssh laptop&lt;/code&gt;). For VSCode is not that convenient since I would need to close the connection,
made a new one to the new host and so on. Surely we could made this simpler, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my home network, my main router is also my DNS server (with Ad Blocking, rules and all kind of fancy things), and that
server resolves my local domain (&lt;code&gt;*.lan&lt;/code&gt;) to LAN IP Addresses, so I can start with a simple config as I had previously:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# .ssh/config&lt;/span&gt;
Host&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;laptop
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;HostName&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;laptop.lan
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, what happens if I'm not at home? I could solve this in several ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I could &lt;code&gt;ping&lt;/code&gt; my router, but that could collide with other networks out there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I could check if my Wifi BSSID is one of the APs at home, but I could also connect via Ethernet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I could check if I can resolve the &lt;code&gt;laptop.lan&lt;/code&gt; address, though this requires network access, but in the end is the one I ended
up using.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;dig&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;+short&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;laptop.lan
&lt;span class="m"&gt;192&lt;/span&gt;.168.1.2&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# At home&lt;/span&gt;

$&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;dig&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;+short&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;laptop.lan
&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Empty result when away from home&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, here comes the &lt;a href="https://man7.org/linux/man-pages/man5/ssh_config.5.html"&gt;&lt;code&gt;Match&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; magic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# .ssh/config&lt;/span&gt;
Host&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;laptop
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;HostName&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;laptop.lan

Match&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;originalhost&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;laptop&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;exec&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;[[ &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;/usr/bin/dig&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;+short&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;laptop.lan&lt;span class="k"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt; == &amp;#39;&amp;#39; ]]&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;HostName&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;laptop.sdn
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using &lt;code&gt;Match&lt;/code&gt; we can replace properties for a defined host using matches. In this ad-hoc example what I did is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Match originalhost laptop&lt;/code&gt;: The connection host need to match &lt;code&gt;laptop&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;exec "[[ $(/usr/bin/dig +short laptop.lan) == '' ]]"&lt;/code&gt;: Execute &lt;code&gt;dig&lt;/code&gt; and try to resolve my LAN's laptop domain name.
This needs to be a successful command for it to match, in this case we compare &lt;code&gt;dig&lt;/code&gt;s output to an empty string to evaluate
if we can resolve the &lt;code&gt;laptop.lan&lt;/code&gt; domain name (check the &lt;code&gt;[[ ]]&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;HostName laptop.sdn&lt;/code&gt; If both rules match, replace the &lt;code&gt;HostName&lt;/code&gt; property with the laptop's SDN domain name.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a pretty easy way to just &lt;code&gt;ssh laptop&lt;/code&gt; wherever I am. I didn't knew about this particular
keyword until today, and it's pretty powerful!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Documentation: &lt;a href="https://man7.org/linux/man-pages/man5/ssh_config.5.html"&gt;ssh_config(5) manpage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>April 2022</title><link href="https://fmartingr.com/blog/2022/05/04/april-2022/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2022-05-04T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name></name></author><id>urn:uuid:39a43fda-3ada-3388-ac0c-e3819567927c</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2022/05/04/april-2022/image-640.png" alt="A picture of a room in my house right now, full of boxes because we&amp;#39;re moving to a new flat."&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the most accurate summary I can give of the last month. This is the first time player 2 and I are moving between
places together, and between the usual work this kind of thing has and some surprises we have had along the way... I didn't
have time for anything else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TV has been set in the living room for... three days? And we haven't used it. I can play a little bit on the Deck when tired,
but usually no more than 20 minutes or so. Reading is limited to that little time before going to sleep, and we've been
so tired that I'm lucky if I manage to finish one chapter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started to catch up with Github and E-Mail yesterday (literally!), hopefully things will normalize in June.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>March 2022</title><link href="https://fmartingr.com/blog/2022/04/01/march-2022/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2022-04-01T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name></name></author><id>urn:uuid:a7d331ce-073d-3bcc-b0ce-4c7f34a98ece</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2022/04/01/march-2022/image-360.jpg" alt="A Japanese Torii gate"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="text-center"&gt;I've started drawing a little on the tablet. I'm awful at it, but it's a relaxing way to pass the time while having a cup of coffee. (Yes, the date is wrong)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- readmore --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This month has been pretty poor in comparision to others, apart from work we had some situation at home that has made us took the decision of moving to another place, so in between looking for a place, the preparations and the undisclosed thing that has made us take this decision I didn't have much time for anything else, and that's why this month's entry is so scarce in content in comparison to other months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we're planning to move in two-three weeks this will be the same for the coming month as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="personal-projects"&gt;Personal projects&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some little progress on &lt;a href="https://github.com/go-shiori"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;go-shiori&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; triaging and bug-fixing. Nothing else worth mentioning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="books"&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started reading &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/68429.The_Well_of_Ascension"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The well of ascension&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started reading &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18939933-1"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Log Horizon #1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read this month:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/58086172-solo-leveling-04"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solo Leveling #4&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gtm-store.com/product/horizon-corazon-de-madre/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Horizon: Corazon de Madre&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; A book from &lt;a href="https://www.gamestribune.com/"&gt;Games Tribune&lt;/a&gt; about Horizon: Zero Dawn (Spanish).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/249469-gigant"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gigant #9&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="tvshows-and-movies"&gt;TVShows and Movies&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Watching &lt;a href="https://beta.crunchyroll.com/series/G79H23W70/ranking-of-kings"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ranking of Kings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Not up to date because I didn't have time. but I may be almost there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="games"&gt;Games&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Started &lt;a href="https://www.xbox.com/es-ES/games/store/marvels-guardians-of-the-galaxy/9pgll77c201j"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marvel's Guardians of the Galaxy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="articles-https//t-me/fmartingr-articles"&gt;&lt;a href="https://t.me/fmartingr_articles"&gt;Articles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.wezm.net/v2/posts/2022/alpine-linux-docker-infrastructure-three-years/"&gt;Alpine Linux and Docker Infrastructure Three Years Later&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://gilest.org/rss-feels.html"&gt;What using RSS feeds feels like&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://jvns.ca/blog/2022/02/20/things-that-used-to-be-hard-and-are-now-easy/"&gt;Things that used to be hard and are now easy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://nebula.app/videos/hai-why-theres-an-empty-skyscraper-in-the-middle-of-times-square"&gt;Nebula&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://dkb.io/post/google-search-is-dying"&gt;Google Search Is Dying | DKB&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sive.rs/plaintext"&gt;Write plain text files&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sive.rs/rand1"&gt;Generate unique random values directly in the database&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.sunfishcode.online/bugs-in-hello-world/"&gt;Bugs in Hello World&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sive.rs/itunes"&gt;The day Steve Jobs dissed me in a keynote&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DJ_Link/status/964124424969637888"&gt;David Amador  on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.psychologyofgames.com/2010/03/framing-and-world-of-warcrafts-rest-system/"&gt;Framing and World of Warcrafts Rest System&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theverge.com/22935074/hundred-rabbits-uxn-roms-preservation"&gt;https://www.theverge.com/22935074/hundred-rabbits-uxn-roms-preservation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://spectra.video/w/1gV9xtPSU6wPHkH4terVDs"&gt;Babycastles Academy: Intro to Uxn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.privateinternetaccess.com/blog/the-fediverse-decentralized-social-media-for-human-beings/"&gt;The Fediverse: Decentralized Social Media for Human Beings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"&lt;a href="https://smitop.com/post/reddit-whiteops/"&gt;Reddit's website uses DRM for fingerprinting&lt;/a&gt;"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>February 2022</title><link href="https://fmartingr.com/blog/2022/03/01/february-2022/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2022-03-01T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name></name></author><id>urn:uuid:97b6b486-433b-34c2-9874-1d13742eb15c</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2022/03/01/february-2022/image-360.png" alt="Me sitting on the couch with my laptop, with a couch laptop table on top of my arms while triaging all shiori issues."&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="text-center"&gt;I'm pretty sure this is how everyone use their laptops at home.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- readmore --&gt;

&lt;h2 id="personal-projects"&gt;Personal projects&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started work on &lt;a href="https://code.fmartingr.dev/fmartingr/dharma"&gt;dharma&lt;/a&gt;, a simple tool to check for broken links, sources and hrefs on a static site to generate a report and potentially allow comparision with a local fpolder to check which files are not included/linked in the static site and can be deleted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A lot of work in &lt;a href="https://github.com/go-shiori"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;go-shiori&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. After I wrote the original maintainer about the project it made me maintainer as well, so I've been making some quality of life fixes, triaging all issues and sorting some stuff here and there. Most of the time I'm just replying issues or reviewing pull requests, but the feeling or moving the project forward is amazing. There's a lot of work to do, though, so I'm grateful the community is there after all this time. I managed to make two releases and screw up only once!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="books"&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/55277893-press-reset"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Press Reset&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/58921971-el-imperio-final"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Final Empire&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/177249-inuyashiki"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Last Hero Inuyashiki&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/58975499-el-umbral-de-lo-siniestro"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Umbral de lo siniestro&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read this month:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/57193-one-piece"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One Piece&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Up to date)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.webtoons.com/en/thriller/hellbound/list?title_no=3598"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hellbound&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Up to date)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/256393-tokyo-revengers"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tokyo Revengers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Volume 2)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/249469-gigant"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gigant&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Volume 8)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/212829-tongari-b-shi-no-atelier"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Atelier of Witch-Hat&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Volume 2)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="tvshows-and-movies"&gt;TVShows and Movies&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ongoing with &lt;a href="https://beta.crunchyroll.com/series/G79H23W70/ranking-of-kings"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ranking of Kings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finished &lt;a href="https://www.disneyplus.com/series/the-book-of-boba-fett/57TL7zLNu2wf"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The book of Boba Fett&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I'd say I liked it... but honestly I didn't. And the only thing that made me watch it through the end is 1) it is Star Wars 2) &lt;span class="spoiler"&gt;Mando&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;As always, &lt;a href="https://nebula.app/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nebula&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://curiositystream.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CuriosityStream&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as daily drivers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Watched the &lt;a href="https://www.primevideo.com/detail/The-Legend-of-Vox-Machina/0O1MH4HMS00EO6XP75LWG5TB89"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Legend of Vox Machina Season 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Harry Potter&lt;/strong&gt; marathon! Only the last two films remain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've not watched/checked on my Youtube feed for the entire month and I've lost the urge to check it out. Now I only check nebula from time to time (because it does not have updates daily) and I'm way happier and tend less to procastinate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="games"&gt;Games&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Continuing with &lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/354240/Please_Dont_Touch_Anything/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please, dont touch anythng!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. We are only two endings from finishing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sort of finished &lt;a href="https://www.nintendo.es/Juegos/Nintendo-Switch/Leyendas-Pokemon-Arceus-1930510.html"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pokemon Legends: Arceus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game was crazy fun with the new catching mechanic, but the end-game is not very well crafted:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The game doesnt teach you to prepare a decent pokemon team&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The difficulty curve is just awful. After some easy battles with 3 pokemon max the last one is a trainer with 6 pokemon, swaps them to take type advantage and heals them to max health. At this point it can easily one shot your team easily if you're not carefu enough. &lt;span class="spoiler"&gt;Which ends up being three combats in a row without healing in between (first vs 6 pokemon, then a legendary, and then the same legendary but angrier) making only two viable strategies: Grinding (which isnt very effective in this game) or just sacrificing Pokemon in each fight because you know its going to kill them. (Which is, in fact, the  recommended method in online guides)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was a lack of love and polish in general as well: secondary mission tracking can be vastly improved, the player should be able to travel between areas without passing through the village, if you give me a secondary mission to get &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; items in each map, at least give me something to track them, since I already have to catch ~250 pokemon at least once, and on top of all, &lt;span class="spoiler"&gt;dont make having those collectibles mandatory for completing the pokedex because one pokemon only show up if you do&lt;/span&gt;.
that seem to be using the same engine as this one)
&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;/rant&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even after all that, I think is a good way to move forward with the pokemon franchise but is very obvious that this game needed more time to be polished and to think some things through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really hope they invest enough time in the next entries in the series since it seems that they share the engine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started &lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/1599340/Lost_Ark/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lost Ark&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh geez, why did I do this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2022/03/01/february-2022/lost-ark.png" alt="My character fishing in Lost Ark"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="articles-https//t-me/fmartingr-articles"&gt;&lt;a href="https://t.me/fmartingr_articles"&gt;Articles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://dkb.io/post/google-search-is-dying"&gt;Google search is dying&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;video&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://yewtu.be/watch?v=QiTene7mHpc"&gt;Anti-Piracy in Nintendo DS Games&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://domlaut.com/icloud-custom-email-domains-should-be-better/"&gt;iCloud+ Custom Email Domains should be better&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.wezm.net/v2/posts/2022/alpine-linux-docker-infrastructure-three-years/"&gt;Alpine Linux and Docker Infrastructure Three Years Later&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://gilest.org/rss-feels.html"&gt;What using RSS feeds feels like&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://jvns.ca/blog/2022/02/20/things-that-used-to-be-hard-and-are-now-easy/"&gt;Things that used to be hard and are now easy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;video&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://nebula.app/videos/hai-why-theres-an-empty-skyscraper-in-the-middle-of-times-square"&gt;Why Theres An Empty Skyscraper In The Middle Of Times Square&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://kevq.uk/gemini-isnt-the-solution-to-the-broken-web/"&gt;Gemini isn't the solution to the broken web&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://wizardzines.com/comics/life-of-a-dns-query/"&gt;Life of a DNS query&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://drewdevault.com/2021/12/28/Dont-use-Discord-for-FOSS.html"&gt;Please don't use discord for FOSS projects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://digiday.com/media/why-facebook-keeps-collecting-peoples-data-and-building-their-profiles-even-when-their-accounts-are-deactivated/"&gt;Why Facebook keeps collecting peoples data and building their profiles even when their accounts are deactivated&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>January 2022</title><link href="https://fmartingr.com/blog/2022/02/01/january-2022/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2022-02-01T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name></name></author><id>urn:uuid:a7ef9f53-d778-32d6-b184-f1533a44fec8</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2022/02/01/january-2022/image-360.jpg" alt="A picture of me resting a book called Press Reset on my legs while looking at the horizon."&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="text-center"&gt;We had amazing holidays this year.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- readmore --&gt;

&lt;h2 id="personal-projects"&gt;Personal projects&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have been working a lot on my notion boards nowadays. Not that I'm better planning what do I do with my time, having everything laying around on different services. So I made simple boards to keep track of stuff. It seems like a stupid thing but sometimes I actually forgot about books, films, games, etc. So having everything there is very helpful to sort out what to read, watch or play next.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2022/02/01/january-2022/notion-games-board-360.png" alt="My notion board for games organisation"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I re-enabled &lt;a href="https://github.com/fmartingr/switch-games-json"&gt;fmartingr/switch-games-json&lt;/a&gt; only to find out that I don't need it anymore! Started this project because of the funny way screenshots on a Nintendo Switch are stored, and turns out you can just connect it through USB to a computer and use the Android File Transfer to get them perfectly sorted in folders with game names.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I worked a bit on &lt;a href="https://code.fmartingr.dev/fmartingr/bazaar"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;bazaar&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. A simple service to extract product information from websites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've started to work on a way to automate some field updating in Notion that I'm calling &lt;strong&gt;AutoNotion&lt;/strong&gt; for now. Ideally this will receive a set of configuration files in &lt;em&gt;yaml&lt;/em&gt; and will allow to make simple updates to database items when some fields change, are missing, etc. Initially this would react to events but sadly it will have to work either doing polling or running on a cronjob caching database information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Forked &lt;a href="https://github.com/fmartingr/shiori"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;go-shiori/shiori&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; since the main one seems unmaintained. I like the simplicity of the project but it is a bookmark manager conceived as an alternative of a read-later service without features for the last. Since I want it to be more like Pocket the plan was to fork it and made it my own but I've written to the original author in case I can be the project's new maintainer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Released &lt;em&gt;0.2.0&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;a href="https://github.com/fmartingr/games-screenshot-manager"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;fmartingr/games-screenshot-manager&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; after giving it some love it clearly deserved, just bits of improvements here and there in preparation for future features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="books"&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/59955909-el-libro-hueco"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;El libro hueco&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. After playing the game I strongly needed to understand everything behind the game. This compendium was amazing for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started reading &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/55277893-press-reset"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Press Reset&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started reading &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/58921971-el-imperio-final"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Final Empire&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/57126185-1984"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1984&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; On my backlog for a long time, and it don't dissapoint at all. Just amazing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/55477870-los-vengadores"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marvel's Must-Have: Avengers Dissasembled&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/55437417-spiderman"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marvel's Must-Have: Universe Spiderman&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/58101976-spiderman"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spiderman Life Story&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ongoing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/57193-one-piece"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One Piece&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.webtoons.com/en/thriller/hellbound/list?title_no=3598"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hellbound&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/312408-solo-leveling-manhwa"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solo Leveling&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/132470-tower-of-god"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tower of God&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/256393-tokyo-revengers"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tokyo Revengers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="tvshows-and-movies"&gt;TVShows and Movies&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finished &lt;a href="https://www.netflix.com/title/80192098"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Money Heist&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; mostly because the Player 2 wanted to watch it. Honestly this final part has been the worst of all series. I would have stopped watching after the first heist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finished &lt;a href="https://www.tvtime.com/en/show/260315"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Orphan Black&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Tatiana Maslany&lt;/em&gt; is just amazing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finished &lt;a href="https://www.tvtime.com/en/show/362696"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Witcher: Season 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Ended up watching everything on a rainy weekend, I'm now even more hyped to read the entire book series, if only I had time for it at the moment...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Up to date with &lt;a href="https://www.disneyplus.com/series/the-book-of-boba-fett/57TL7zLNu2wf"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The book of Boba Fett&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I'm not digging it much, except for episode five which I loved for obvious reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also watched a few things from &lt;a href="https://nebula.app/"&gt;Nebula&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://curiositystream.com/"&gt;CuriosityStream&lt;/a&gt; this month now than I am detoxifying from YouTube. This are some interesting channels that come to mind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://nebula.app/notjustbikes"&gt;Not Just Bikes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://nebula.app/lowspecgamer"&gt;LowSpecGamer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://nebula.app/extracredits"&gt;Extra Credits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://nebula.app/storymode"&gt;Story Mode&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://nebula.app/minutebody"&gt;Minute Body&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://nebula.app/kentobento"&gt;Kento Bento&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="games"&gt;Games&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finished &lt;a href="https://www.nintendo.es/Juegos/Programas-descargables-Nintendo-Switch/Hollow-Knight-1125772.html"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hollow Knight&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. My relationship with Hollow Knight can be easily represented by &lt;a href="https://cluelesshero.com/post/655919454629330944/325-toxic-relationship-help-i-just-cant-get-out"&gt;this comic&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2022/02/01/january-2022/hollow-knight.png" alt="Clueless Hero: Toxic Relationship"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started &lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/1444480/Turing_Complete/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Turing Complete&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on my backlog for a while, only to play some kind of different puzzle game. If only I were better at it...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Continuing with &lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/354240/Please_Dont_Touch_Anything/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please, dont touch anythng!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. We managed to get a lot of new endings thanks to notes we had from previous runs. Only five endings to finish it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started &lt;a href="https://www.nintendo.es/Juegos/Nintendo-Switch/Leyendas-Pokemon-Arceus-1930510.html"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pokemon Legends: Arceus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. This is the right way to evolve the Pokemon franchise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="articles-https//t-me/fmartingr-articles"&gt;&lt;a href="https://t.me/fmartingr_articles"&gt;Articles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.wesleyac.com/posts/web3-centralized"&gt;Web3 is centralized&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://jvns.ca/blog/2022/01/05/why-might-you-run-your-own-dns-server-/"&gt;Why might you run your own DNS server&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://tonsky.me/blog/syncthing/"&gt;Computers as I use to love them&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://threema.ch/en/blog/posts/md-architectural-overview"&gt;Threema Multi-Device: An Architectural Overview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.thegingerviking.com/the-right-to-delete-fakerjs-fragile-nature-open-source/"&gt;The right to delete: how faker.js exposed the fragile nature of open source culture, again&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notes.nicfab.it/post/xmpp/xmpp/"&gt;XMPP: the secure communication protocol that respects privacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://boilingsteam.com/steam-deck-developer-kit-impressions/"&gt;Steam Deck Developer Kit Impressions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.inthemesh.com/archive/secure-scuttlebutt-facebook-alternative/"&gt;Scuttlebutt, A Decentralized Alternative To Facebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=29916899"&gt;Ask HN: What do you think of the Wordle guy not monetizing it?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.haschek.at/2019/the-curious-case-of-the-RasPi-in-our-network.html"&gt;The curious case of teh RasPi in our network&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;nebula.app&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://nebula.app/videos/story-mode-spiderman-writer-breaks-down-the-games-opening"&gt;Spider-Man Writer Breaks Down the Game's Opening&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://cygnusentertainment.com/2022/01/19/big-fish-getting-bigger/"&gt;Big Fish Getting Bigger&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;nebula.app&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://nebula.app/videos/simonclark-how-the-tongan-shockwave-caused-a-tsunami"&gt;How the Tongan shockwave caused a tsunami&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;youtube via Piped&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://piped.kavin.rocks/watch?v=2uEqYw-N8uE"&gt;Git's Best And Most Unknown Feature&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>December 2021</title><link href="https://fmartingr.com/blog/2021/01/01/december-2021/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2022-01-01T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name></name></author><id>urn:uuid:c1563f1f-163b-35ee-9589-32884debe520</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2021/01/01/december-2021/image-360.jpg" alt="The Elantris book openend in page 610 over my laptop in my parent&amp;#39;s house desktop"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="text-center"&gt;This is a pretty good summary of the month.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- readmore --&gt;

&lt;h2 id="personal-projects"&gt;Personal projects&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wrote &lt;a href="https://github.com/fmartingr/nudge"&gt;nudge&lt;/a&gt; an evening after internet went down at home. Would be a way of controlling if we have an available internet connection using multiple sources so our Home Assistant instance can reset the router using an smart outlet/ssh connection, since it seems that my &lt;a href="https://firewalla.com/products/firewalla-gold"&gt;Firewalla Gold&lt;/a&gt; keep giving me headaches: just last month when my apartment building lost internet the local DNS resolver stopped working just because it didn't have internet, breaking some of my home services... and now after not correctly recovering when my internet connection went down for a few minutes. I just can't recommend this thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Related to this I need to work on a failover solution for when the internet is down for a very long time and we're not home, maybe a 4G router of some sort? I don't know.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now that I'm reading way more in physical editions I'm working on some services to check stock/prices of my personal book wishlist. Following a bit of the mainsteam buzzwords I want it to be event driven hexagonal design, so far I've splitted it into 6 microservices but they would probably be more. I need to start a board of some sort to start working on this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="books"&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/29242989-elantris"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elantris&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read two short stories from &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/40552794-arcanum-ilimitado"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arcanum Unlimited&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; related to the Elatris world (The Sel System): &lt;strong&gt;The emperor's soul&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;The hope of Elantris&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And... I'm all in with comics/manga/manhwa:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Up to date with &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/57193-one-piece"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One Piece&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;! What an incredible journey. I've read up to the volume edited here in Spain and to the latest available chapter on the Jump! mangazine app. I can watch memes and everything one piece because I'm not going to spoil myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ongoing wit &lt;a href="https://www.webtoons.com/en/thriller/hellbound/list?title_no=3598"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hellbound&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. A chapter per week, sticking to the free tier for now so I can consume it slowly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/23689723-los-dioses-mienten"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The God's Lie ()&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/59654559-la-barca-de-los-canarios"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Canary Boats ()&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started several series:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On volume 2 of &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/249469-gigant"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gigant&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;strong&gt;Hiroya Oku&lt;/strong&gt;, one of my favouirte manga authors. If you like &lt;em&gt;seinen&lt;/em&gt;, please give &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/77126-gantz"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gantz&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; a look.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On volume 2 of &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/169755-platinum-end"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Platinum's End&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;strong&gt;Takeshi Obata&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Tsugumi Ohba&lt;/strong&gt;, authors of other jewels like &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/52807-death-note"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Death Note&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/52005-bakuman"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bakuman&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (though I still haven't read that last one).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On volume 1 of &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/212829-tongari-b-shi-no-atelier"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Atelier of the Witch-Hat&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On volume 1 of &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/312408-solo-leveling-manhwa"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solo Leveling&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On volume 1 of &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/132470-tower-of-god"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tower of God&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="tvshows-and-movies"&gt;TVShows and Movies&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finished &lt;a href="https://www.tvtime.com/en/show/367146"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hawkeye&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. What a fun way to end the year from Disney. If this is the base level for everything coming from the MCU into 2022 I'm all in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tried but Dropped: &lt;a href="https://www.tvtime.com/en/show/299139"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Magicians&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It was like watching a bunch of high schoolers doing stupid things, hope the books are better that this though I'm not sure if I would ever try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started &lt;a href="https://www.tvtime.com/en/show/362696"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Witcher: Season 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Only the first episode to check if it was a summary of some sort, and I remembered the tale vagely, maybe it is included in &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/40603587-the-last-wish"&gt;The last wish&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started &lt;a href="https://www.tvtime.com/en/show/260315"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Orphan Black&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Watched a few episodes a long while ago but didn't remember why I stopped it. After reading around that &lt;em&gt;Tatiana Maslany&lt;/em&gt; was going to be &lt;em&gt;She-Hulk&lt;/em&gt; I decied to start over again with it, her performance is just brilliant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started &lt;a href="https://www.tvtime.com/en/show/391625"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ranking of Kings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Watched the first episode to check what the fuss is about, seems a mix between different and interesting, so I'm waiting the drop on Crunchyroll so I can continue with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Watched &lt;a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/die-hard/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Die Hard&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Perfect for Christmas day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course, watched &lt;a href="https://letterboxd.com/film/spider-man-no-way-home/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spider-man: No way home&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. 10/10. Would remove my memories of it and watch it again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="games"&gt;Games&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ongoing with &lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/367520/Hollow_Knight/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hollow Knight&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I'm surprised my Switch is still intact after so many deaths.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/blog/2021/01/01/december-2021/hollow-knight.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2021/01/01/december-2021/hollow-knight-360.jpg" alt="Hollow Knight screenshot"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="articles-https//t-me/fmartingr-articles"&gt;&lt;a href="https://t.me/fmartingr_articles"&gt;Articles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Video) &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/sXxcPxjwLj8"&gt;Window to the World Demo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Video) &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/sajcUVDDBU8"&gt;Inside Japan's Abandoned Coin Lockers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ar.al/2021/12/16/saying-goodbye-to-an-old-friend/"&gt;Saying goodbye to an old friend&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://small-tech.org/videos/small-technology/"&gt;Small technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://elliott.computer/pages/web0.html"&gt;My first web0 website!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.jetpens.com/blog/Japan-s-Paper-Culture/pt/998"&gt;Japan's paper culture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.jim-nielsen.com/2021/for-the-love-of-the-web/"&gt;For the love of the web&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>November 2021</title><link href="https://fmartingr.com/blog/2021/12/01/november-2021/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2021-12-01T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name></name></author><id>urn:uuid:c5652c16-0570-32b9-9607-f8e1b4418435</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2021/12/01/november-2021/image-360.jpg" alt="Ramen dish from Ramen Kagura in Madrid, Spain"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="text-center"&gt;Mandatory visit to Ramen Kagura when visiting Madrid.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- readmore --&gt;

&lt;h2 id="books"&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;All in with comics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ongoing with &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/57193-one-piece"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One Piece&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: Volume 93, I'm almost there! A weekend without internet did marvels to my progess here :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read &lt;a href="https://www.panini.es/shp_esp_es/marvel-must-have-civil-war-smust001-es01.html"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marvel's Must Have: Civil War&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started &lt;a href="https://www.webtoons.com/en/thriller/hellbound/list?title_no=3598"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hellbound&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to check if it's any better than the TV Show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also read &lt;a href="https://www.viz.com/ask-iwata"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ask Iwata&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="tvshows-and-movies"&gt;TVShows and Movies&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Finished" &lt;a href="https://www.crunchyroll.com/es-es/one-piece"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One Piece&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: Reached the end of the official spanish dub. We've replaced this with &lt;a href="https://www.primevideo.com/detail/0HBVL22LMA40B0XBY30RUOC9EH/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bones&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Up to date with &lt;a href="https://tv.apple.com/us/show/for-all-mankind/umc.cmc.6wsi780sz5tdbqcf11k76mkp7"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For all mankind&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Already finished and with a nice cliffhanger for the next season. Didn't though I would enjoy a drama this much. I may be getting old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Watched &lt;a href="https://www.netflix.com/title/81435684"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arcane&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought I wouldn't enjoy this one since I'm not a League of Legends player (I've only player a couple matches like ten years ago...?) but I &lt;em&gt;loved&lt;/em&gt; it. The art style is top-notch, the story, even going a bit fast at some points it was well explained through amazing visual compositions and the soundtrack is on par as well, loved how they used the mix of visuals and music to tell how &lt;span class="spoiler"&gt;Ekko and Jinx played in their fight at the end of the show&lt;span&gt;. Can't wait for more seasons or other shows in this universe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm assuming that people that know the world heroes from the games would know who's &lt;span class="spoiler"&gt;not going to die&lt;/span&gt; so I'm glad I'm not in that group on this one (though you could mostly tell anyway...). The same way I didn't get a lot of easter eggs on the show that current players mostly did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Watched &lt;a href="https://www.netflix.com/title/81256675"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hellbound&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a note, I only watched the first chapter in the usual way you would watch a TV show (1x in VO). The rest I put on the English dub and a 1.5x speed so I could go though it offscreen while I did other things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not sure about why but I didn't like this one at all, and I wouldn't watch anything else if Netflix release more in the future. It's a very good premise but not very enjoyable on a TVShow I guess, everything happens so quickly and the impact didn't feel real. I started reading the manwha to check if it is any better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started &lt;a href="https://www.disneyplus.com/series/hawkeye/11Zy8m9Dkj5l"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hawkeye&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next from the Marvel universe. It seems pretty simple with a lot of comedy so far. Argument-wise doesn't seem like much at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="games"&gt;Games&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started &lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/367520/Hollow_Knight/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hollow Knight&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Had this on my backlog for years and since the Steam Deck is now officialy delayed and I won't get mine until next summer as the soonest I started with it the other day (so I haven't gotten very far). The art style is amazing and I still need to get used to the controls, but everyone says that this is a masterpiece so I had to start at some point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Still ongoing with &lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/736260/Baba_Is_You/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Baba is you&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Since we don't play much we are going veeeery slowly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tried &lt;a href="https://www.xbox.com/es-ES/games/marvels-avengers"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marvel's Avengers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; but it had heavy frame drops on my PC so I just stopped trying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="articles-https//t-me/fmartingr-articles"&gt;&lt;a href="https://t.me/fmartingr_articles"&gt;Articles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://erickhun.com/posts/nft-misconception-image-arent-on-blockchains/"&gt;NFT misconception: JPEG aren't on the Blockchain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.farhadg.com/my-genius-roommate"&gt;How My Genius Roommate Changed My Perspective&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(video) &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/esIL1W_QBns"&gt;Mew's Origins: A Story of Secrets, Rumors &amp;amp; Legends Ft. mafmoefoe (Pokemon)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(video) &lt;a href="https://youtube.com/watch?v=bJMFXdLQRyo&amp;amp;feature=share"&gt;Nintendo 64DD: The REAL Reason it FAILED &amp;amp; Nintendo's Would-Be Plans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.simplethread.com/20-things-ive-learned-in-my-20-years-as-a-software-engineer/"&gt;20 Things I've Learned in my 20 Years as a Software Engineer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/2018/09/how-to-build-a-lowtech-website/"&gt;How to Build a Low-techWebsite?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://hynek.me/articles/semver-will-not-save-you/"&gt;Semantic Versioning Will Not Save You&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/what-is-web3/"&gt;Web3  A vision for a decentralized web&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://drewdevault.com/2021/11/16/Python-stop-screwing-distros-over.html"&gt;Python: Please stop screwing over Linux distros&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://zachholman.com/posts/only-90s-developers/"&gt;Only 90s Web Developers Remember This&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(video) &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/CCOdQsZa15o"&gt;The Houses that Can't be Built in America - The Missing Middle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://notes.eatonphil.com/implementing-zip-in-go-unzipping.html"&gt;Implementing ZIP in Go&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ruurtjan.medium.com/understanding-kafka-with-factorio-74e8fc9bf181"&gt;Understanding Kafka with Factorio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://surfingcomplexity.blog/2021/11/28/i-have-no-idea-what-im-doing/"&gt;I have no idea what Im doing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://batsov.com/articles/2021/11/28/firefox-is-the-only-alternative/"&gt;Firefox is the Only Alternative&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.asciinema.org/post/smaller-faster/"&gt;4x smaller, 50x faster  asciinema blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>How I organize my Home Assistant automations</title><link href="https://fmartingr.com/blog/2021/11/30/how-i-organize-my-home-assistant-automations/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2021-11-30T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name></name></author><id>urn:uuid:285cad25-43a3-3729-a8b3-de5d576f3c3e</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Automations in Home Assistant are the best thing after the cocoa discovery, I use them a lot for many different things and I'm always wondering how to solve the &lt;em&gt;first world problem&lt;/em&gt; of the day. The hassle with it is that apart from a list and the search there are not much more options to filter, and when your automations grow it became a bit of a pain finding what you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- readmore --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the other day I decided to follow a "path" approarch to my automations. I'm using a subject, an action or element and then a description to name them:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;(subject) / (action/element) / (short description)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2021/11/30/how-i-organize-my-home-assistant-automations/automations-list-360.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This way &lt;em&gt;Turn on the air purifier at night&lt;/em&gt; became &lt;code&gt;air purifier / auto / turn on at night&lt;/code&gt; and I can filter by &lt;code&gt;air purifier /&lt;/code&gt; to get all the automations related to the air purifier, the specific automatic behaviour by &lt;code&gt;/ auto&lt;/code&gt; (for this and other subjects), etc:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2021/11/30/how-i-organize-my-home-assistant-automations/automations-filtered-360.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is so much convenient than before though I'm sure I will keep iterating on this, at least now my list is ordered and I can easily find anything I want to toggle or edit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wonder how other Home Assistant users handle their automations, if you by any reason read this and have a better way, &lt;a href="/about/"&gt;please let me know!&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>Home Assistant battery levels at a glance</title><link href="https://fmartingr.com/blog/2021/11/15/home-assistant-battery-levels-at-a-glance/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2021-11-15T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name></name></author><id>urn:uuid:6a9e8b17-4ad4-3e57-b288-8c26bc1ceecb</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was talking recently about how many Zigbee devices are too many and how the most troublesome thing you can have is batteries dieing on you at the same time. If you install several devices at once and have it's batteries dead at the same it it's a bit of a hassle going to each one and replacing it (depending where you have them and how difficult is to replace).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- readmore --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It came to me that if we could see the battery status of devices easily on a card this can be at least addressed by knowing which batteries are most discharged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As context, since I'm usually playing with devices I use number as identifiers. For example, my motion sensors are named &lt;em&gt;Motion Sensor #X&lt;/em&gt; (where &lt;em&gt;X&lt;/em&gt; is an increasing number). This way it's ID is &lt;code&gt;motion_sensor_1&lt;/code&gt; and it's entities &lt;code&gt;(entity type).motion_sensor_X_(attribute)&lt;/code&gt;. I use this nomenclature everywhere so I can easily identify entities with the internal search (and because you need to have a method, always!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So. I can get all entities that represent a battery by searching for &lt;code&gt;_battery&lt;/code&gt; but I have no real means of translating that search into a card without &lt;a href="https://github.com/thomasloven/lovelace-auto-entities"&gt;a third party component called &lt;strong&gt;Auto entities&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This card allows to &lt;em&gt;automatically populate lovelace cards with entities matching certain criteria&lt;/em&gt; which is what I'm looking for, and it's pretty easy to use as well!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a card on my dashboard with this configuration to display battery statuses accross my entities:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;type&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;custom:auto-entities&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;card&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;type&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;entities&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;title&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;Battery statusq&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;state_color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;show_header_toggle&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;include&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p p-Indicator"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;entity_id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;*_battery&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;sort&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;method&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;state&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;numeric&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;reverse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;show_empty&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;unique&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="l l-Scalar l-Scalar-Plain"&gt;entity&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is how it looks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2021/11/15/home-assistant-battery-levels-at-a-glance/card-screenshot-640.png" alt="Auto entities displaying the battery levels of the different devices at home"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This card is very powerful, I already have a few other ideas on how to use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check it out: &lt;a href="https://github.com/thomasloven/lovelace-auto-entities"&gt;Auto entities card&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>October 2021</title><link href="https://fmartingr.com/blog/2021/11/02/october-2021/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2021-11-02T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name></name></author><id>urn:uuid:501d21b8-9067-3106-86b5-d94e4af78582</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2021/11/02/october-2021/image-360.jpg" alt="A picture of myself from the back while I try to take a picture of a nice river reflection from a building"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="text-center"&gt;A ninja picture of me taking a picture&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- readmore --&gt;

&lt;h2 id="books"&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ongoing with &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/57193-one-piece"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One Piece&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: Volume 67+&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm completely on fire with this. I bought all pending volumes and now I just need to get up until the last volume. I forgot many things of these last story arcs so I'm enjoying it a lot more now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finished &lt;a href="https://www.webtoons.com/en/fantasy/dice/list?title_no=64"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DICE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm actually not sure if I liked the ending or not. Since I re-started the series not so long ago it seemed rushed to me, but it could be only a perception issue. I didn't like the character development on this last "games" but it surprised me how everything unfolded in the end. There's actually a last "epilogue" chapter that I haven't read yet and should be available today. Not sure what it could contain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway! It has been good overall, character development has been good (with some new characters and stories along the way), powers and usage are actually pretty interesting as well even though there are some very overpowered habilities in there. If you like similar stories you won't miss with this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm sorry &lt;del&gt;if&lt;/del&gt; this fails as a review, but keep in mind that I started reading it years ago, so it is pretty difficult to get a complete picture to evaluate it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="tvshows-and-movies"&gt;TVShows and Movies&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;For lunch and dinner time &lt;a href="https://www.crunchyroll.com/es-es/one-piece"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One Piece&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: Reached Water 7 saga.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finished &lt;a href="https://www.disneyplus.com/series/the-bad-batch/4gMliqFxxqXC"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Star Wars: Visions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one ended up lower than my expectations, mostly because the first episode was one of the (if not the) best. I love Trigger episodes becuase I loke their style and storytelling, but in most episodes there was a lightsaber here and there, and while I can understand that it's difficult to opt-out using force sensitive characters when they allow you to create and tell an official Star Wars story, I would have loved more without it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; believe I've said it more than once on other shows... these are inmense worlds with &lt;strong&gt;a lot&lt;/strong&gt; of possibilities and we end up recurring to the basics because it is what please us the fanbase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finished &lt;a href="https://www.disneyplus.com/series/what-if/7672ZVj1ZxU9"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marvel's What if...?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just amazing, and renewwd for a season two! I need to find out if some or more of this stories are available in the comics, I already bought one on a whim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next stop: Hawkeye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started &lt;a href="https://tv.apple.com/us/show/for-all-mankind/umc.cmc.6wsi780sz5tdbqcf11k76mkp7"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For all mankind&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My discovery of the month. I'm already at the last episode of the second season and I'm loving this show! At first I though that I wouldn't like it because it didn't have much &lt;em&gt;sci-fi thingies&lt;/em&gt; but in the end it has just enough for it to be an amazing show. It's more a drama than anything else but you end up hating or empathizing with the characters, their decissions and eveything around them. 100% recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dropped &lt;a href="https://www.disneyplus.com/series/y-the-last-man/6GhSTQBktm34"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Y: The last man&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FX cancelled the series so there's no point anymore. Someone commented out that the comics are good so that could be the way to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="games"&gt;Games&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finished &lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/1456880/ElecHead/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elec Head&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been waiting on this since I saw a trailer somewhere on the internet and bought it the moment it released. It was crazy fun! Level design is amazing and the simple mechanics are just right. The only thing that game me the creeps is that there are some thing that you may just notice by pure chance. Since it's cheap and only a few hours of time, it's an obvious recommendation!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2021/11/02/october-2021/elechead-360.png" alt="I achieved all Elec Head achievements. It wasn&amp;#39;t easy at all!"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here we go again... &lt;a href="https://www.nintendo.es/Juegos/Nintendo-Switch/Animal-Crossing-New-Horizons-1438623.html"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Animal Crossing: New Horizons&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final update is coming and the player 2 and myself have come back to our islands to do some preparations. Since it's the last update this is most likely the last time I will get hooked to the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Still ongoing with &lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/736260/Baba_Is_You/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Baba is you&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="articles-https//t-me/fmartingr-articles"&gt;&lt;a href="https://t.me/fmartingr_articles"&gt;Articles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tech&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://fasterthanli.me/articles/beware-the-google-password-manager"&gt;Beware the Google Password Manager&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.andrewjvpowell.com/articles/we-are-solar-powered/"&gt;We are now Solar Powered&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://naehrdine.blogspot.com/2021/09/always-on-processor-magic-how-find-my.html"&gt;Always-on Processor magic: How Find My works while iPhone is powered off&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.theverge.com/22684730/students-file-folder-directory-structure-education-gen-z"&gt;File not found: Professors are struggling to teach Gen Z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://slate.com/technology/2021/10/facebook-unfollow-everything-cease-desist.html"&gt;Facebook banned me for life because I help people use it less&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/october-2021-facebook-outage/"&gt;Understanding how Facebook disappeared from the Internet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/androiddev/comments/q4nltn/ads_are_now_able_to_bypass_google_play_to_install/?utm_source=share&amp;amp;utm_medium=web2x&amp;amp;context=3"&gt;Ads are now able to bypass Google Play to install apps WITHOUT user consent.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-wMU8vmfaYo"&gt;Why was Facebook down for five hours?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gaming&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jmAbunjFBkA"&gt;asobu meets indies #1: NamaTakahasi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/mmxFaCVYMCc"&gt;Japan's Arcades are DISAPEARING --- Is it time to say goodbye?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spanish&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.anaitgames.com/articulos/mercurysteam-empleados-condiciones-trabajo/"&gt;Empleados de MercurySteam hablan sobre las condiciones de trabajo del estudio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bJMFXdLQRyo"&gt;Nintendo 64DD: The REAL reason it FAILED&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Literature&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sive.rs/bp"&gt;Considerate book pricing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>Storing data in Node-Red flows using contexts</title><link href="https://fmartingr.com/blog/2021/10/11/storing-data-in-node-red-flows-using-context/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2021-10-11T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name></name></author><id>urn:uuid:bac5ae30-20fe-3979-b315-360f02670198</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been adding some automations to my Home Assistant recently so it can inform us of takeaway menu changes for local restaurants. We have a few favourites and they usually offer different options each day so checking for updates and notifying us via our Telegram bot is pretty easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- readmore --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I didn't want to use any library or custom program/service to analyze the page I'm relaying this kind of work to the Node-Red service in my Home Assistant instance. It's a server that is always working, easy to set up, work and iterate from, and I already have some integrations in place for notifications and other QoL, so it seemed like a 110% win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite having used Node-Red for various purposes along the years I usually delegated state to different services, databases or the filesystem. Not sure why I didn't check if Node-Red had something built-in-- which of course it had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Node-Red has this concept of &lt;em&gt;context&lt;/em&gt;. By default a context is stored in memory only, and you can get/set values from a node or from function nodes very easily:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2021/10/11/storing-data-in-node-red-flows-using-context/node-red-change-node-360.png" alt="Node-Red Change node allows to make changes in contexts"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can also edit contexts programatically from function nodes using:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;msg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;contentSize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mf"&gt;123&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;// From another node&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nx"&gt;flow&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;set&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;menuContentSize&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;msg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;contentSize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kd"&gt;var&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;value&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;flow&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;menuContentSize&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my case I wanted the data to persist service restarts and Node-Red provides a context store filesystem based which stores changes in memory and persists them to disk every 30 seconds, more than enough for my use case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To enable it we need to modify the &lt;code&gt;settings.js&lt;/code&gt; file of the Node-Red installation and add the appropriate &lt;code&gt;contextStore&lt;/code&gt; parameters:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="hll"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;// ...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;contextStorage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;state&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;      &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;module&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;localfilesystem&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;      &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;base&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;state&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;// This will store the data in ~/.node-red/state,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;},&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;default&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;module&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;memory&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="w"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;},&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="w"&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;// ...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this example I created a new context store called &lt;em&gt;state&lt;/em&gt; using the filesystem module I talked before and additionally I set up the storage in a custom directory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This way I can have two context stores: one in memory (the default) and one to store my custom states. You can create more for your use cases but keep in mind that you need to select a different &lt;code&gt;dir&lt;/code&gt; for each of them so they wont collide. For more information check &lt;a href="https://nodered.org/docs/api/context/store/localfilesystem#implementation-details"&gt;the implementation details&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to select an store to use you have a dropdown in the change node:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2021/10/11/storing-data-in-node-red-flows-using-context/node-red-change-node-dropdown-360.png" alt="Node red change node with dropdown selection"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Or use the third argument&lt;code&gt;flow.set(key, value, store)&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;flow.get(key, store)&lt;/code&gt; to select it programatically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This allows for this very simple state checks in my case but allows for way more complex behaviors right out of the box.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm a very big fan of Node-Red. And I can use that so get notified of takaway menu changes now. Talk about a first world problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;References:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://nodered.org/docs/user-guide/context"&gt;Node-Red: Context&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://nodered.org/docs/api/context/store/localfilesystem#options"&gt;Node-Red: Local Filesystem context store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>September 2021</title><link href="https://fmartingr.com/blog/2021/10/02/september-2021/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2021-10-02T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name></name></author><id>urn:uuid:22d63820-f121-35ca-b5ab-1f6b5b9f7dc8</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2021/10/02/september-2021/image-360.jpg" alt="A picture of a beach about 45 minutes walking from my home"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="text-center"&gt;I love having this at _somewhat_ walking distance. Can you spot my shadow?&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- readmore --&gt;

&lt;h2 id="projects-personal"&gt;Projects &amp;amp; Personal&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I manage to fulfill my "development needs" so much at work that I try to use my spare time in other hobbies nowadays. Not that I don't have pending things to do, I just don't feel like spending much time on the computer after work anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The few things I have been doing are looking for an alternative to the Firewalla at home. I'm thinking on installing opnsense on the Firewalla SoC cause it just don't really suit my needs. The problem is that opened a whole set of questions again on how to setup and sort all network devices at home, how I'm going to manage (server and networking side) the public and private services I have and so on. I would like to try it before just giving up on my current router directly, so I need to setup this on a VM and start playing with it to check if it does the essential things I want it to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing I have been spending time theses days is sorting out my note and habits management. I tend to scribble on paper and just forget about it for current projects, but sometimes I write something that should be more persistent over time. So good luck past/present/future me figuring out how to handle that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the habit side I'm trying out &lt;a href="https://habitify.me"&gt;Habitify&lt;/a&gt; just to know how much of my work/personal/leisure time I spend "correctly". That's the best thing I found to track this kind of "tasks", but I don't like the subscription model at all... if anyone has a suggestion that is either self-hosted or single-payment please &lt;a href="/about/"&gt;contact me&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, as always, I've been improving my Home Assistant instance with new things. But that's the usual once you enter this world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="books"&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Up to date with &lt;a href="https://www.webtoons.com/en/fantasy/dice/list?title_no=64"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DICE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ongoing with &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/57193-one-piece"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One Piece&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: Volume 56.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finished &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/14061957-ruin-and-rising"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ruin and Rising&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talk about a long road... finally finished the trilogy. This final sprint has been a bit rough, and it almost made me read some pages a bit "diagonal" just to end it. Got really boring at the end if I must say. I do not plan on reading anything else for this saga.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started reading &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/48562648-jap-n-con-jam-n"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Japn con Jamn&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been on my bookshelf for a year or so now. I just couldn't read anything Japan related because it reminded me a lot of the time I spent there. But well, after two years it's time to go on. Sadly it seems that it's not in anything but Spanish...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="tvshows-and-movies"&gt;TVShows and Movies&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;For lunch and dinner time &lt;a href="https://www.crunchyroll.com/es-es/one-piece"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One Piece&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Watched &lt;a href="https://es.hboespana.com/series/rick-and-morty/3be6e070-1044-4740-8478-2936de705e4c/season-5/2d8a1c0b-ad1c-46e2-aedd-475390b2d8da"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rick and Morty: Season 5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What an amazing season! The first two chapters were incredible, but the last two... oh my! I'm really glad I didn't spoil myself on social because I have enjoyed it a lot. I waited until all chapters were available in HBO so I could watch all chapters in a row. And oh my, I loved it! Not sure why people complain about this season -of course it has better and worse episodes- but overall it has been awesome. The worst part is waiting for the next season!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started &lt;a href="https://es.hboespana.com/series/raised-by-wolves/607e39f2-6d7c-4d1a-85d2-278ad1e270a1/season-1/1c7157fc-ad39-46fe-a44f-3972e51a80e6"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raised by wolves&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had it in store for some time and only two episodes in... it has everything I like: Sci-Fi, Dystopian setting, robots, etc. But... it is a bit weird. Maybe I don't understand the message of something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started &lt;a href="https://www.disneyplus.com/series/the-bad-batch/4gMliqFxxqXC"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Star Wars: Visions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's finally here! As a fan of Japanese animation is awesome to watch some of them allowed to create a history on a Star Wars related setting. I don't know what to expect but so far I liked every episode, specially the one from Trigger... their art style and storytelling is amazing. Though I would've like to know more of each history, I'm happy that episodes are 15 minutes long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started &lt;a href="https://www.disneyplus.com/series/what-if/7672ZVj1ZxU9"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marvel's What if...?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another that I was eager to watch this month and I managed to keep up to date until this point. I'm loving it so far and it seems that everything until this point is going to converge in the final episodes in one hell of a battle. I really hope they do more seasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started &lt;a href="https://www.disneyplus.com/series/y-the-last-man/6GhSTQBktm34"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Y: The last man&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wasn't expecting much from this one, but a friend told me about it and I put it off focus while I was doing some chores. It's average for my taste but at least the premise seems... interesting? I don't know. Let's see how it goes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="games"&gt;Games&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finished &lt;a href="https://www.nintendo.es/Juegos/Game-Boy-Advance/The-Legend-of-Zelda-The-Minish-Cap-267486.html"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The legend of Zelda: The Minish Cup&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This game have grown old incredibly well. Mechanics, gameplay and even graphics are incredible. And I'm telling this in 2021 from a game that released in 2004, 17 years ago!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I played it on original hardware, a tuned GameBoy Advance SP with a FunnyPlaying LCD screen, and even if I liked the experience I had to play it through  short sessions (maybe 30-60m tops) because the handhelds are so tiny that my fingers hurt a bit after some time. Also the SP is so narrow that my hands are almost touching. I'm not sure if I will play everything here, maybe only games that can be played for 10-15m (like Rhythm Tengoku) but I have my eye on Golden Sun 1&amp;amp;2 now... I'm glad I have emulation machines everywhere and a brand new &lt;a href="https://www.epilogue.co/product/gb-operator"&gt;GB Operator&lt;/a&gt; that I can use to play on a bigger screen and backup my games and saves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finished &lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/698780/Doki_Doki_Literature_Club/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Doki Doki Literature Club!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not going to say anything. Just play it. It's four hours or so of gameplay. Play it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Still ongoing with &lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/736260/Baba_Is_You/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Baba is you&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We didn't manage to get much time to play, but we're slowly going through it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="articles-https//t-me/fmartingr-articles"&gt;&lt;a href="https://t.me/fmartingr_articles"&gt;Articles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Developers&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://medium.com/@ighor/i-unlocked-nvidia-geforce-now-and-stumbled-upon-pirates-dc48a3f8ff7"&gt;I unlocked NVIDIA GeForce NOW and stumbled upon Pirates&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://adrian.gaudebert.fr/blog/post/four-months-of-horizontal-game-production"&gt;Four Months of Horizontal Game Production - Blog | Adrian Gaudebert&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://engineering.fb.com/2021/07/14/security/whatsapp-multi-device/"&gt;How WhatsApp enables multi-device capability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://drewdevault.com/2021/09/23/Nitter-and-other-internet-reclamation-projects.html"&gt;Nitter and other Internet reclamation projects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://h2x.sh/apple/"&gt;Start using tools again&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;em&gt;leaving Apple's ecosystem&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://habr.com/en/post/579714/"&gt;Disclosure of three 0-day iOS vulnerabilities and critique of Apple Security Bounty program&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://people.freebsd.org/~gallatin/talks/euro2021.pdf"&gt;Serving Netflix Video at 400Gb/s on FreeBSD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://drewdevault.com/2021/09/27/Let-distros-do-their-job.html"&gt;Let distros do their job&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gamedeveloper.com/console/playdate-pulp-zero-to-video-game-in-60-seconds"&gt;Playdate Pulp: Zero to video game in 60 Seconds&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://peguero.xyz/blog/google_and_facebook_i_am_facilitating_packet_filtering_to_block_your_tracking.html"&gt;Google and Facebook, I am facilitating packet filtering to block your tracking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://endtimes.dev/why-you-should-dither-images/#how-does-dithering-reduce-file-sizes"&gt;How does dithering reduce file sizes?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Games&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.thegamer.com/how-ionizing-particle-outer-space-helped-super-mario-64-speedrunner-save-time/"&gt;How An Ionizing Particle From Outer Space Helped A Mario Speedrunner Save Time&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.atlasobscura.com/articles/why-we-picture-bombs-as-round-black-balls-with-a-burning-wick"&gt;Why we picture bombs as round black balls with a burning wick&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[video] &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yiw6_JakZFc"&gt;Can YOU fix climate change?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>August 2021</title><link href="https://fmartingr.com/blog/2021/09/12/august-2021/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2021-09-12T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name></name></author><id>urn:uuid:97e43982-a82e-3947-846d-b9cda130b026</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/blog/2021/09/12/august-2021/image.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2021/09/12/august-2021/image-360.jpg" alt="My birthday cake!"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="text-center"&gt;Imagine waking up to this every day... sadly it only happens on vacation.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- readmore --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really quick update since I've been either on vacation, visiting or being visited by family. Slowly going back to normal now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="books"&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.webtoons.com/en/fantasy/dice/list?title_no=64"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DICE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/57193-one-piece"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One Piece&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: Volume 41 and beyond!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Struggling to finish &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/14061957-ruin-and-rising"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ruin and Rising&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finished &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/6612476-death-note---another-note"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Death Note: Another Note&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All I can say is do not bother with it. I just want to read the original saga to compensate...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="tvshows-and-movies"&gt;TVShows and Movies&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;For lunch and dinner time &lt;a href="https://www.crunchyroll.com/es-es/one-piece"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One Piece&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finished &lt;a href="https://www.disneyplus.com/series/the-bad-batch/4gMliqFxxqXC"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Star Wars: The Bad Batch&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What a finale! It was really sad to see &lt;span class="spoiler"&gt;all that destruction on Kamino&lt;/span&gt; directly on a show, but we all knew that happened... It didn't have me hooking (or even paying attetion sometimes) but I want to know what's in store for the next season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="games"&gt;Games&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;On hold with &lt;a href="https://www.nintendo.es/Juegos/Nintendo-Switch/The-Legend-of-Zelda-Skyward-Sword-HD-1923575.html"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The legend of Zelda: Skyward Sword HD&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The controls are just awful... It's a shame because it has some interesting things in there but I just can't get on with it :(&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started &lt;a href="https://www.nintendo.es/Juegos/Game-Boy-Advance/The-Legend-of-Zelda-The-Minish-Cap-267486.html"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The legend of Zelda: The Minish Cup&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Got my geared up GameBoy Advance SP loaded for the travel, and despite the RNG regarding the luck stones this game has aged really well in my oppinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Still around with &lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/736260/Baba_Is_You/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Baba is you&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="articles-https//t-me/fmartingr-articles"&gt;&lt;a href="https://t.me/fmartingr_articles"&gt;Articles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Art&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://medium.com/@gameboynerd/the-art-of-game-boy-games-67cb8bb31d98"&gt;The Art of GameBoy games&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Videogames&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[twitter thread] &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/JoelBurgess/status/1428008041887281157?s=20"&gt;Skyrim oral history - treasure fox&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[twitter thread] &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/The_Opponent/status/1430204227067027458?s=20"&gt;StarFighters76 map contributions on GameFaqs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Engineering&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://palant.info/2021/08/02/data-exfiltration-in-keepa-price-tracker/"&gt;Data exfiltration in Keepa Price Tracker&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[twitter thread] &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/KevEdwardsRetro/status/1424457994553765891"&gt;NES Development in 1988&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.pixelstech.net/article/1628407126-Will-nil-==-nil-be-true-in-GoLang"&gt;Why nil == nil be true in GoLang&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HLWY7fCXUwE"&gt;It's just emulation! The challenge of selling old games&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ctrl.blog/entry/homenet-domain-name.html"&gt;What domain name to use for your home network&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://jacobkiers.net/hod/"&gt;HTML over DNS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://mkorostoff.github.io/1-pixel-wealth/"&gt;Wealth, shown to scale&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[video] &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ftr9yY-YuYU"&gt;Can dogs tell the time?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[twitter thread] &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dguido/status/1424921645483966466"&gt;Scooter stolen with an Airtag inside it&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[video] &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SVvF_Qyq5F0"&gt;Are video games a global pandemic?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>July 2021</title><link href="https://fmartingr.com/blog/2021/08/01/july-2021/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2021-08-01T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name></name></author><id>urn:uuid:97e7c909-765a-3043-9f64-07f1b6d89a5b</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/blog/2021/08/01/july-2021/image.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2021/08/01/july-2021/image-360.jpg" alt="My birthday cake!"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="text-center"&gt;On the good days that actually seems like summer we get some beaufiful landscapes like this.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- readmore --&gt;

&lt;h2 id="projects"&gt;Projects&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ever since I ended up on my current job I spend less and less time with the computer in the after-work hours, real life  stuff and my numerous other hobbies tend to maintain me busy, so I've spent very little time with these things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/fmartingr/switch-games-json"&gt;switch-games-json&lt;/a&gt; I've started work on how people could contribute new entries to it. I have a working proof of concept and I have to import all currently data present on the internets before releasing it publicly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/fmartingr/games-screenshot-manager"&gt;games-screenshot-manager&lt;/a&gt; Planning a big refactor since I use this very regularly and it &lt;a href="http://gallery.fmartingr.com"&gt;works very well&lt;/a&gt; but it can be way faster that it is now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;notion-to-ical&lt;/strong&gt;: I'm working on a little service to convert a Notion calendar database into an iCal feed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;3D Printing. More like 3D calibrating since I didn't manage to find the proper attributes to print some pieces corretly, and since it a bit of trial and error it's taking its time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="books"&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.webtoons.com/en/fantasy/dice/list?title_no=64"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DICE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/57193-one-piece"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One Piece&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: Volume 27 and beyond!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finished &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/14061955-siege-and-storm"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Siege and Storm&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started reading &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/14061957-ruin-and-rising"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ruin and Rising&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last book of the Ghrisaverse trilogy, series seems a bit average until this point but it manages to keep me wanting to know what will happen next. I just hope this one doesn't end in a cliffhanger or with anything pending so I can start reading other series after that, since I've seen that there are other books based on this world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="tvshows-and-movies"&gt;TVShows and Movies&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;For lunch and dinner time &lt;a href="https://www.crunchyroll.com/es-es/one-piece"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One Piece&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ongoing with &lt;a href="https://www.disneyplus.com/series/the-bad-batch/4gMliqFxxqXC"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Star Wars: The Bad Batch&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This became an off-series, I just let it run in background while I do other things and I manage to keep track easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finished &lt;a href="https://www.disneyplus.com/series/loki/6pARMvILBGzF"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Loki&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What a show, what a show! I loved the ending (though I expected a different character to appear) and their performance was just amazing, can't wait to see how this threads into the films and the next season. The MCU is doing an amazing work in this department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="games"&gt;Games&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finished! &lt;a href="https://rhythmheaven.fandom.com/wiki/Rhythm_Tengoku"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rhythm Tengoku (&lt;em&gt; / Rhythm Heaven&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got all gold medals and beat the final drum minigame, and that's a wrap! I'm not going to put myself through unnecessary pain by doing all the perfect scores. It was ver difficult and a lot of fun, specially since I could play it in short sessions through the months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="text-center"&gt;
  &lt;video autoplay loop muted id="background" width="640" height="360"&gt;
    &lt;source src="./rhythm-tengoku.webm" type="video/webm"&gt;
    &lt;source src="./rhythm-tengoku.mp4" type="video/mp4"&gt;
  &lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stopped &lt;a href="https://store.playstation.com/es-es/product/EP0700-CUSA14054_00-OPWSK00APPLI0000"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One Piece: WORLD SEEKER&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href="http://gallery.fmartingr.com/PlayStation-4-ONE-PIECE-WORLD-SEEKER.html"&gt;screenshot  gallery&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I stopped playing this one mostly because I wasn't enjoying it much, but also because I don't know where this is set in the One Piece storyline and I didn't want to spoil myself. I will continue with it once I reach the last One Piece volume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Still around with &lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/736260/Baba_Is_You/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Baba is you&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We still have this on our pipeline, Player 2 seems to enjoy it since loves puzzles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started &lt;a href="https://www.nintendo.es/Juegos/Nintendo-Switch/The-Legend-of-Zelda-Skyward-Sword-HD-1923575.html"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The legend of Zelda: Skyward Sword HD&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course. I didn't progress much and I totaly hate the sword mechanic until the point that I almost drop it at the beginning... but I want to see it through the end since it's the first in the series, time will tell if I complete it or just finish the story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="articles-https//t-me/fmartingr-articles"&gt;&lt;a href="https://t.me/fmartingr_articles"&gt;Articles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Engineering&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/golang/go/commit/7d7c6a97f8"&gt;First go language commit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://drewdevault.com/2021/07/04/Is-GitHub-a-derivative-work.html"&gt;Is GitHub a derivative work of GPL'd software?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://leveluppp.ghost.io/benchmarks-in-go-can-be-surprising/"&gt;Bencharmks in Go can be surprising&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://michael.stapelberg.ch/posts/2021-07-10-linux-25gbit-internet-router-pc-build/"&gt;25 Gigabit Linux internet router PC build&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://drewdevault.com/2021/07/28/The-next-YAML.html"&gt;My wish-list for the next YAML&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Videogames&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/golang/go/commit/7d7c6a97f8"&gt;A 23-Year Perfectionist Journey to Localize the Obscure 'Bahamut Lagoon'&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[video] &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/9Ki-kH751_8"&gt;How the Game Boy almost ruined Nintendo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[video] &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/HyzD8pNlpwI"&gt;The ultimate Game Boy Talk (33c3)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2021/07/museum-obtains-rare-demo-of-id-softwares-super-mario-bros-3-pc-port/"&gt;Museum obtains rare demo of id Software's Super Mario Bros 3 PC port&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://arstechnica.com/features/2021/07/collectors-are-as-confused-as-you-are-about-that-1-56m-super-mario-64-sale/"&gt;Collectors are as confused as you are about that $1.56M Super Mario 64 sale&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2021/07/playdate-preview-you-wont-believe-how-fun-this-dorky-179-game-system-is/"&gt;Playdate preview: You wont believe how fun this dorky, $179 game system is&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Traveling&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[video] &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4EQ34L05pOw"&gt;Visiting All The Main Tourist Attractions In Kyoto - Completely Empty&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;News&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/TrungTPhan/status/1414966594179006466"&gt;Disney+ success tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://nuclearmonster.com/2021/07/ethan-flibitijibibo-lee-may-retire-from-programming-due-to-valves-proton/"&gt;Ethan flibitijibibo Lee May Retire from Programming Due to Valves Proton&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://eand.co/this-isnt-a-heatwave-it-s-a-dying-planet-ac1c9eb529d1"&gt;This Isnt a Heatwave  Its a Dying Planet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[video] &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/9zDrp4pncDs"&gt;I Get MAD | Blizz's DISGUSTING Anti Customer Behavior EXPOSED&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content></entry><entry><title>June 2021</title><link href="https://fmartingr.com/blog/2021/07/01/june-2021/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2021-07-01T00:00:00Z</updated><author><name></name></author><id>urn:uuid:826f6f5c-85e0-3e8a-af24-5a4aaa564bc0</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/blog/2021/07/01/june-2021/image.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/2021/07/01/june-2021/image-360.jpg" alt="My birthday cake!"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="text-center"&gt;This was technically last month, but celebrated on June 1st. Happy cake day to me!&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- readmore --&gt;

&lt;h2 id="books"&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Up to date with &lt;a href="https://www.webtoons.com/en/fantasy/dice/list?title_no=64"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DICE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The end is getting closer and closer, or so it seems!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/10194157-shadow-and-bone"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shadow and Bone&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finished the first book of the Ghrisaverse recently, it reminded me of the &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/44134-the-black-magician-trilogy"&gt;Black Magician Trilogy&lt;/a&gt; though a lot of things happen on this book actually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The magic system is a bit... weird. It isn't explained much and though they say it can be infinite the different level in power of characters is not very well expressed with very clear differences in the characters that show up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite that it's fun to read because the storytelling is good and you start getting yourself inmersed in the life of the characters from the very beginning even if it's a very clear &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hero&amp;#39;s_journey"&gt;hero's journey&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started reading &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/14061955-siege-and-storm"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Siege and Storm&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Continuing from the previous one, I haven't gotten very far on this one but even in five chapters they already untangled the first book cliffhanger, expecting more to happen and adding a bit of backstory to previously non-explained things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started reading &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/57193-one-piece"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One Piece&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yes!&lt;/strong&gt; I finally got a good pack of volumes from a second-hand online store and have tons to read. I haven't actually read the comics from the very beginning before and I'm getting surprised of some changes between the manga and the anime. I'm very happy I managed to get the collection on my shelf already after all this time, this is going to keep me busy for a few months :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/55978796-horizon-zero-dawn-vol-1"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Horizon Zero Dawn Volume #1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Got this one looking around art books online, and it was quite a surprise that they deciced to tell the history of Horizon's world in this format as well. The history follows a side-quest character shown in the game after the game's ending and while it's not very deep it presents new things to the world that would be present on the new game releasing this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="tvshows-and-movies"&gt;TVShows and Movies&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lunch time:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.primevideo.com/detail/0HBVL22LMA40B0XBY30RUOC9EH/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bones&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do we keep choosing shows this long!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.crunchyroll.com/es-es/one-piece"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One Piece&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Player's 2 idea (never expected this, not complaining though!). Since episodes are very short (~20m) she get enough time to eat. The bad part is that I need to read the comics fast enough so anime doesn't catch up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ongoing with &lt;a href="https://www.disneyplus.com/series/the-bad-batch/4gMliqFxxqXC"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Star Wars: The Bad Batch&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very little has happened until this point, they need to start adding real conflict to the show because is getting a bit boring for my taste :(&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started &lt;a href="https://www.disneyplus.com/series/loki/6pARMvILBGzF"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Loki&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A-mazing. The first chapter is a bit of a introduction to everything so not much is it there, but since this is going to be a 6 episode only show I'm expecting the climax will come in episode 4-5 (4 aired yesterday but I don't have the time to watch it until tomorrow, so shush!). It's actually very good, the mix of &lt;em&gt;seriousness&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;humor&lt;/em&gt; is very well done (and performed!) in the show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="games"&gt;Games&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finished &lt;a href="https://www.playstation.com/en-us/games/horizon-zero-dawn/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Horizon: Zero Dawn&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href="http://gallery.fmartingr.com/PlayStation-4-Horizon-Zero-Dawntm_-Complete-Edition.html"&gt;screenshot gallery&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finished both the main story and the Frozen Wilds DLC, I enjoyed the story quite a lot to be honest. I like dystopian worlds and getting to know &lt;em&gt;how did we get there&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game was overall fun though repetitive (all missions are either kill or track, in essence). Side missions doesn't seem to expand the story in a very meaningful way so I just kept to the main storyline and did some sides that were either on my way or gave good rewards. I also had a lot of problems with my inventory, I got the resource expansion satchel the earliest I could because I'm a loot hoarder but after a few hours into the game I was always full and had to sell, scrap or throw stuff around to make room for items (specially blue ones because I didn't knew if I would need them for new gear or quests) and that persisted until the very end of the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The side collectibles around the world were just  too many. When I finished the game I only had 4 text datapoints from the world, out of a bazillion. I want to know more about the Lore of the game but that's just ridiculous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from that, the art, storytelling, voice-acting, music department, etc was awesome and really immersive. The only thing I missed while playing is a good sound system to help with the immersion, but well, that's just a first world problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Still in pain: &lt;a href="https://rhythmheaven.fandom.com/wiki/Rhythm_Tengoku"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rhythm Tengoku (&lt;em&gt; / Rhythm Heaven&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have get gold medals up until the fourth tier, and I'm stuck on the rap game... I may be half way through it, more or less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started &lt;a href="https://store.playstation.com/es-es/product/EP0700-CUSA14054_00-OPWSK00APPLI0000"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One Piece: WORLD SEEKER&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href="http://gallery.fmartingr.com/PlayStation-4-ONE-PIECE-WORLD-SEEKER.html"&gt;screenshot  gallery&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Got this as a birthday present and I'm painfully going though it. I'm just playing because the story is supposed to be an Oda's original, but it just seems a bunch of different mechanics thrown together to make a game with One Piece's assets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Started &lt;a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/736260/Baba_Is_You/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Baba is you&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Player #2 and I started couch-playing this cause we both like puzzle games, one takes the controller and we dig through the levels. I love the premise of the game and how simple interactions in the map change everything, and how player 2 and I look at the puzzles from different perspectives finding more than one solution to each level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="articles-https//t-me/fmartingr-articles"&gt;&lt;a href="https://t.me/fmartingr_articles"&gt;Articles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Videogames&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[video] &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/n0NJz0iA37k"&gt;The complete story of Square (part 1)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[video] &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=y8iLmKBlvUE"&gt;The Unexpected Success of Horizon Zero Dawn | 3 Years Later (Retrospective)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[video] &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=h9tLcD1r-6w"&gt;The Making of Horizon Zero Dawn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[video] &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/tKH0x21rj1Y"&gt;Japan's Game Preservation Crisis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://medium.com/@obskyr/the-secret-origin-of-the-action-rpg-254a180079dd"&gt;The Secret Origin of the Action RPG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.vice.com/en/article/qj83yp/final-fantasy-remasters-reignite-controversies-over-pixel-art"&gt;Final Fantasy Remasters Reignite Controversies Over Pixel Art&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[video] &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MspqDuq5OZY"&gt;How Nintendo Failed Into Super Mario Kart | The Story Behind The Super Nintendo Classic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hacking&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[video] &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/4ckjr9x214c"&gt;Mining Bitcoin on the Game Boy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[video] &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7ybybf4tJWw"&gt;Doom on an IKEA TRDFRI lamp!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://gir.st/blog/greenpass.html"&gt;What's Inside the EU Green Pass QR Code?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TV Shows&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[video] &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/Umu19quwinI"&gt;The Strangely Melancholy Ending to The Good Place  Brandon Sanderson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Programming&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://medium.com/@felipedutratine/how-to-organize-the-go-struct-in-order-to-save-memory-c78afcf59ec2"&gt;How to organize the go struct, in order to save memory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[video] &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/iKBs9l8jS6Q"&gt;Top 100 3D Renders from the Internet's Largest CG Challenge | Alternate Realities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[video] &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wxWK0zb-9k8"&gt;Manga Kissa: Life in Japans Smallest Rooms | ASIAN BOSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content></entry></feed>